<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second report of Doctor Iohn Faustus. Containing his appearances, and the deedes of Wagner. / VVritten by an English gentleman student in VVittenberg an Vniuersity of Germany in Saxony. Published for the delight of all those which desire nouelties by a frend of the same gentleman</title>
            <author>English gentleman student.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10715</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115012</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850232</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850232</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178202</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13519)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178202)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1485:8b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second report of Doctor Iohn Faustus. Containing his appearances, and the deedes of Wagner. / VVritten by an English gentleman student in VVittenberg an Vniuersity of Germany in Saxony. Published for the delight of all those which desire nouelties by a frend of the same gentleman</title>
                  <author>English gentleman student.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Abell Ieffes for Cuthbert Burby, and are to be sold at the middle shop at Saint Mildreds Church by the stockes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Inspired by the German "Ander theil" but essentially an independent text. Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I4, K2 (A1, A2 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178202:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178202:1"/>
            <p>THE SECOND REPORT of Doctor Iohn Fauſtus, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his appearances, and the deedes of Wagner.</p>
            <p>VVritten by an English Gentleman ſtudent in VVittenberg an Vniuerſity of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many in Saxony.</p>
            <p>PVBLISHED FOR THE DELIGHT of all thoſe which deſire Nouelties by a frend of the ſame Gentleman.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by Abell Ieffes, for Cuthbert Burby, and are to be ſold at the middle Shop at Saint Mildreds Church by the Stockes. 1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:178202:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178202:2"/>
            <head>VNTO THEM WHICH WOVLD know the trueth.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is plaine that many thinges in the firſt book are meere lies, for proofe marke this: it is ſaide that it is tranſlated, ſo it is, and where it is word for word: But I haue talked with the man that firſt wrote them, hauing them from <hi>Wagners</hi> very friend, wherein he ſaith manie thinges are corrupted, ſome added <hi>de nouo,</hi> ſome canceld and taken awaie, and many were augmented. As for addition to the Coppy is there where <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> diſputeth of the numbers of Hels, and ſome other diſputations: And let a man marke them duely, they ſhall finde them I will not ſaie childiſh, but certainly ſuperficiall, not like the talk of Diuels, where with foldings of words they doe vſe to dilate at large, and more ſubtell by farre. But as for his Obligation and the moſt part, it is certaine they are moſt credible and out of all queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II</head>
               <p>For to take away a doubt, whether there were ſuch a man, which is generally a thing not beleeued, <hi>I</hi> aſſure them this, that there was, and it is prooued thus, nor is <hi>Germany</hi> ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen but that the trueth of theſe thinges following may be founde if any ſuſpect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III</head>
               <p>Firſt there is yet remaining the ruins of his houſe, not farre from <hi>Melanchtons</hi> houſe as they call at the townes end of <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg,</hi> right oppoſite to the Schooles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:178202:3"/>
               <head>IIII</head>
               <p>Secondly there is yet to be ſeene his tree, a great hollowe Truncke, wherein he vſed to reade <hi>Nigromancy</hi> to his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, not farre from the towne in a very remote place, which I thinke is ſufficient teſtimony to any reaſonable eare. And enquire of them which haue beene there, ſee if they will not affirme it. Notwithſtanding I doe not goe by theſe meanes I, to entreate men to beleeue, for <hi>I</hi> care not whether they do or no, but onely to certifie you of the trueth as I my ſelfe would bee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V</head>
               <p>Next, his tombe is at <hi>Mars</hi> Temple, a three miles beyond the Citty, vppon which is written on a Marble ſtone by his owne hand, this Epitaph, which is ſomewhat old by reaſon of his ſmall skill in grauing.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="epitaph">
                  <body>
                     <p>Hic iaceo Iohannes Fauſtus, Doctor diuini iuris in digniſsimus, qui pro amore magiae Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicae ſcientiae vaniſsimè cecidi ab amore Dei: O Lector pro me miſerrimo damnato homine ne preceris, nam preces non iuuant quem De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us condemnauit: O pie Chriſtiane memento mei, &amp; ſaltem vnam pro infiducia mealachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulam exprime, &amp; cui non potes mederi, eius miſerere, et ipſe caue.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Stone was found in his ſtudy, and his wil was fulfilled, and he lieth betwixt a heap of three and thirty fir trees in the fort of the Hill in a great hole where this is erected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:178202:3"/>
               <head>VI</head>
               <p>If theſe will not ſerue, then ſhall you heare the teſtimonie of a learned man <hi>Iohn Wierus, cap.</hi> 4. <hi>libro</hi> 1. <hi>de magis infamibus.</hi> Which I haue tranſlated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Fauſtus</hi> borne at <hi>Kundling</hi> a little village, learning Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke at <hi>Graconia,</hi> where he was openly taught, and exerciſed it.</p>
               <p>In ſundry places of <hi>Germany,</hi> with the admiration of many and with manifold lies, fraud, and illuſions, with vaine vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and promiſes but could doe nothing: one example I wil ſhew to the Reader, vppon this condition, that he will paſſe his faith firſt to me that he will not imitate him: Then reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth he one of his knaueries, how he tooke vpon him to make no haire grow vppon a mans face, and tooke away with a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which <hi>I</hi> will not name, both the beard that he had and all the ſkinne, cauſing ſuch infla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mations in his face that it burned all ouer cruelly. This he committed being taken at <hi>Batoburg</hi> vppon the banke of the riuer <hi>Moſa</hi> hard vppon the boundes of <hi>Gelderland:</hi> Another (ſaith this learned Phiſition) not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to me, hauing a blacke bearde, the reſt of his face ſomewhat darke and ſwarte, witneſsing melancholy (for hee was ſplenaticke) when he came to <hi>Faustus,</hi> who redily ſaide: Truely I thought you had beene my Familiar, ſtraight waie marking your feete, whether long and crooked nailes ſtook out of them: So likening this man to the Diuell, which hee thought had come vnto him, which Diuell he was wont to cal <hi>Sorarius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VI</head>
               <p>For his death in the ſame place, thus ſaith he: At length hee was found in a Village of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> by his bed ſide ſtarke dead, and his face turnde backewards, and the midnight before, the houſe was ſhaken as it is reported. Thus farre he, an Authour not to bee doubted of, and approoued through Chriſtendome of ſingular and exact iudgement, as appeareth by his writings of the like argument confutation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>VII</head>
               <p>More in the ſame place he ſaith: That a ſchoolemaiſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb facs="tcp:178202:4"/> the <hi>Goſlaryens,</hi> inſtructed of <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the Magitian, or rather <hi>Infauſtus</hi> his euill doctrine, learned a way how the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell might be bound by ſpell on a glaſſe, who as you may ther reade was ſo affrighted, that lying one whole yeare ſpeeches, at thend he ſpake of his feare and diuels appearance, and then hauing receiued his chriſtian rites died.</p>
               <p>As for the Author this Doctor <hi>Wier,</hi> doubt you not of his credite, for he is alledged of the very ſingulareſt ſchollers, as the beſt that euer wrote in that argument. We haue a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of our owne countrey, maiſter <hi>Reignold Scot</hi> Eſquier, that doth vniuerſally quote him as his chiefe and eſpeciall helpe in his diſcouery of Witchcraft, yea and hee teſtifieth of him not without good deſart, ſaying: I. Bode in his lawyerly Phiſicke reaſoneth contrarily, as though Melancholye were fartheſt of from theſe old women whom we call Witches. And the moſt famous and noble Phiſician <hi>Iohn Wier</hi> for his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that behalfe: Loe where he calleth him the moſt famous Phiſitian as he was then certainly, in the diſcouery of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, lib. 3. Cap. 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>IX</head>
               <p>Thus farre I haue ſette downe that you may knowe and perſwade your ſelues ſo farre as you ſee iuſt cauſe by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Vale.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:178202:4"/>
            <head>THE SECOND REPORT OF DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Iohn Fauſtus.</head>
            <opener>In nomine aeternae &amp; ſemperuiuae maieſtatis, Amen.</opener>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Spectatum admiſsi riſum teneatis amici.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octor <hi>Iohn Fauſtus</hi> whoſe parentage howſoeuer hitherto informed, is knowen to be baſe, his father when he was at the beſt, but the ſonne of a poore Farmer, his Mother the daughter of one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame condition, borne in a ſmall village called <hi>Kundling</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> brought vp in literature at <hi>Gracouia,</hi> after at <hi>Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> whoſe life made him famous, and death notorious: being thus tormented and torne in péeces, at the time appointed bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Diuels and him, mooued by this example woefull and lamentable enough, the hearts of the Students and Schollers which where witneſſes of his diſtraughture, that with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward terrour of conſcience vexed and tormented, they departed and declared the whole volumes of his deteſtable life, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Tragedy was thus acted, were not knowen. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Wagner</hi> his familiar ſeruaunt vnto whom hée hadde committed the ſecrets of his boſome, and had intimated vnto him what euer his foure and twenty years familiarity with the black Art, and more blacke Diuels hadde taught him: Hée after the death of his thus ſlaine Maſter muſing at euery thing thus done, euery thing thus done being wonderfull: (as men doe whome feare makes paſſionate and meditation of former loſſe, vrgeth a latter augment of freſh ſorrowes:) in a diſtraughtfull furye (the company of Students being departed, which were eie witneſſes of the Doctors lamentable end) conuayed himſelfe vnto his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Library, viewing with ſorrowfull eies the onely Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his life, the diſputations betwixt him and <hi>Mephoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philes,</hi> his aunſweres and demaunds, and elſe whatſoeuer que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions mooued or diſputed off betwixt the Diuels and him, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials of his Heauens and Hells voyages, his conueaunce with many the like comicall iourneis. The boy of a ſoddaine fell into a déepe conſidering of his former meriments, ſports and delights,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:5"/> in ſo much that in this conceipt he flung out of this ſtudy, as if hée meant to bury the remembraunce of theſe matters by contempte and negligence: comming into the ſame Hall wherein his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters lateſt Tragedy was perfourmed, ſighing for his want, hée remembred (for as then he lately read it) how that one Article to the which his Maiſter had bound <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> was, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death he ſhould be a ſpirite in nature and eſſence as others were. The Wag at this began to ſmile (oh how ſuch thinges ſéeming pleaſaunt make fooles harts merry) conceiuing with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe how to make his once Maiſter become his man, and to haue the number of his ſpirituall followers doubled, ſcorning the a lone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attendaunce of one ſeruaunt. To this therefore he determined a time for the raiſing of his Maiſters ſpirite: and therewith he fel to reade earneſtly of other matters, ſo long that he began to leaue as wearied and wearied began to muſe. Sodainely the aire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to receiue an alteration and chaunge with a thicke foggye miſte, as if it would haue ſhutte vp the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>red day from mans view, the windes raged, the thunder lifted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p his voice aboue the common ſtraine, haile and raine immediatly following, and all theſe but the ordinary preſages of an appearing Spirite. At this <hi>Kit</hi> began to tremble, not as afraide of that which came, but ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with inward horrour of conſcience, thinking that no other time had béene appointed to be his doomes day. Sodainly (for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſuch haps are ſodain) the dores ſlew open as if they would haue fled from flying, and in all pompe entred as it were the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of a Comedy, a fellow ſo ſhort and litle as if hée ſhould be of one year, and yet not ſo briefe as ill fauored, in his hands a Club, on his head a Crowne of Lawrell, riding vppon a low Mule, his name was <hi>Gomory</hi> a ſtrong and mighty Duke, the ruler of ſixe and twenty Legions: next and next in brauery appeared <hi>Volac</hi> a great Gouernour, in the ſhape of a Boy with winges like an Angell of Hell, ſéeming to bee of olde ruſty iron, riding vppon a Dragon with foure heads, in his hands he held a flaming Torch to giue light to the after-commers and beholders: next after him appeared <hi>Aſmoday</hi> a King mightye and puiſſant ragged and brizled like a Bore on foote, bearinge a banner or a launce. After him iſſued <hi>Lucifer</hi> the King of the <hi>Orient</hi> with the foure Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches of his dominions, betwixt them were two mighty Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels
<pb facs="tcp:178202:5"/> which drew in a fiery Cart Doctor <hi>Iohn Fauſtus,</hi> whome if reaſon had not better ruled <hi>Wagner</hi> would haue ſaluted, for ſo naturall was his ſemblaunce, ſo liuely his countenaunce, as if it had eyther beene a new <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> or not the olde murthered <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> but the feare which his maiſters harme put him in, caſt him beſides the renewing of his olde acquaintance, after theſe came diuers others with trumpets and excellent melody.</p>
               <p>This right maruailous triumph thus preſented, each one did his humble obeyſaunce, the beſt beginning (though good there were none) and in the end with huge tumult and ecchoing of tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets they crowned him a King, which when they had done, with the like ceremonies they conuayed out againe the Doctor whom his wretchednes made a King, and his new King-ſhip nothing. <hi>Wagner</hi> ſtarted as if he had now begunne to maruaile, amazed at this merry Enterlude, hauing recouered his memory againe, he began ſoftly to ſpeake to himſelfe in ſuch like manner. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Is this (quoth he) the honour my Maiſter hath in Hell? Is this the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence with which the Féends infernall vſe to entertaine ſuche gueſtes? O yée Spirites of Hell, and yée euen now reuiued Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of great <hi>Limbus,</hi> from whence haue you drawne this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary humanity, is it to ſkorne poore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> or to mocke <hi>Wagner</hi> that you ſhew ſuch reuerence to a vile abiect, what then woulde they doe to <hi>Wagner</hi> who is worthy to haue a fitter ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt then their King?</q> At theſe words he bluſht excéedingly, and began to rage very grieuouſly with his conſciences terrour, and with ſome few teares repenting his irreligious concluſion, roſe vp from the ground, and ſuppoſing it to be but an illuſion dreame, or a temptation, or elſe ſome conceite procéeding from his moiſte and melancholicke fantaſie, ouerpreſt with too many vapors, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp by continuall thought into his Pores: wherefore hee went forthwith into the ſtréetes, (ſo much he diſtruſted himſelfe) and demaunded whether it rainde, hailde, or thundered, and it was aunſwered that it neither raind, haild, nor thundered. <hi>Wagner,</hi> albeit he was newly reuiued from a feare, and ſcarcely throughly wakened from this his great terrours, yet with this comicall ieſt his decayed ſpirites began to recouer their olde ſtrength and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, turning theſe great braueries of Diuels into a meriment, and his conceiued fear into a méere fanſie. This was the firſt time
<pb facs="tcp:178202:6"/> that euer <hi>Fauſtus</hi> appeared vnto his ſeruaunt <hi>Wagner,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited this vnto his companions as a matter of great truth and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle moment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Hovv certaine drunken Dutchmen vvere abuſed by theyr owne conceite and ſelfe imagination, of ſeing the grand Doctor, Doctor Fauſtus. CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>IT ſhall not be impertinent (my very good friends) to declare as I am bound by a Tranſlatours duety, to ſhew what theſe my Dutch friends and ſtudents haue imparted vnto me, not for that I will be a King of your hearts to commaund you to beléeue, but that you may with the reſt of the Hiſtory conceiue the common opinion of him in the vulgars beliefe here in Germany, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch the like illuſions before pretended. About the ſame time, the next yeare wherein <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was thus handled betwixt ſixe and ſeauen a clock in the morning, the fiue and twentith day of Iune, 1539 there chaunced certaine Schollers to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of nine, and fiue other Marchants (called of them <hi>Copſhmen</hi>) two being Engliſh, to walke abroad to a little village within foure Engliſh mile (which is about one of theirs) of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> called <hi>Shaftsburg</hi> to the intent to make merry, whither béeinge come they were excéeding pleaſaunt, as Dutchmen are, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they be at their good Béere, for they are men very impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of thirſt, wherewith the Italian mocks them ſaying:
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Germani multos poſſunt tolerare labores,</l>
                     <l>O vtinam poſsint tam bene ferre ſitim.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto which they merrely aunſwere.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Vt nos dura ſitis, ſic vos Venus improba vexat,</l>
                  <l>Lex lata eſt Veneri Iulia, nulla mero.</l>
               </q>
               <p>So long they druncke, that at laſt they came to be within a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of druncke, fetching ouer the <hi>Green nine Muſes</hi> ſo often at ſundry drafts, till they began to be excéeding merry and pleaſant, til it being time to depart, ſo they ſet out for <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within a mile or ſuch a matter of the Cittye, they came to a thicke Groue called of them the <hi>Phogelvvald</hi> which is <hi>Birdes VVood</hi> in Engliſh, a place ſomewhat delightſome aboue anye there abouts, ſituated vppon a toppe of a very high Hill, but the
<pb facs="tcp:178202:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> armes of it ſpread themſelues ſomwhat lower into the neighbour vallies and meddowes, full of very fine Chriſtalline brookes and ſpringes, which running through the large rancks of trées empty themſelues into the <hi>Elue,</hi> a Riuer which kéepes his current by <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> in this place in a faire Sommer ſun-ſhine day, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together a great number of countrey maides ſeruants, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the female ſexe, which they call <hi>Phogels</hi> (Birds) vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there reſort in ſuch like daies, a great number of ſchollers to méet with theſe Birds, which exerciſe <hi>Venery</hi> either for pleaſure, but indéede ſeldome but for gaine, with whom when they haue daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a great while (after ſome odde tune, as after that which they call <hi>Robinſons delight,</hi> but more truly a <hi>ieſt,</hi> though ſomewhat tolerable) ſome 20. or 30. or 40. couple together, then here ſteps out one couple, and here another, and get them to ſuch odde cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as their continuall practiſe dooth make knowne: on the ſame day wherein this merry company were wandring, who if I ſhould not much erre, I durſt ſay they were moſt déeply drunk, being a Sun-ſhining day and haue no other way to paſſe to <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg,</hi> but onely by this <hi>Phogelvvald</hi> where they determined to be luſty with ſome of the <hi>Phogels,</hi> they came at length to theſe fore-named places, where as to them it ſéemed ſundry Women dancing, and amongſt them diuerſe Schollers, and verely they déemed <hi>Magiſter Doctor Fauſtus</hi> likewiſe, and ſéeing diuerſe maids ſtanding idle ſo many as would fit there many, they went to take them by the hands, and as their order is ſaluting them, to hope about or two (for all the high <hi>Dutchmens</hi> dances ſtands vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hopping, turning, winding, and ſuch odde geſture) and as they ſéemed they danced at great leaſure till this ſaide <hi>Fauſtus</hi> came to them, requeſting them not be amazed, for that it was reported he was dead, aſſuring them in very déede he was not in this world, but had chaunged it for a better, which if it did pleaſe them hee would ſhew vnto them, wher betwixt their delights and his were no compariſon, at his requeſt they were all contented, and he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the formoſt, brought them down into a faire pleaſant gréen, whereon in ſtead of certain flowres grew Pots ful of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt béere, which they taſted on, finding them as good as any that euer they drunk in their whole liues, &amp; farther into a moſt rich &amp; ſumptuous pallace, wherin as they ſéemed they dwelt many daies with great
<pb facs="tcp:178202:7"/> mirth and pleaſure, til at length one more full of curteſie than the reſt thanked maiſter <hi>Fauſtus</hi> for his good entertainement, at which wordes ſoddainely was heard ſo great a noiſe and howling eſpecially of the poore Doctor, who was immediatly reared vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Aire, accompanied with ſuch a ſort of blacke cloudes and miſtes, as therewith not onely the skie, but alſo their eyes were mightely darkened, and they brought into a déepe Cauern, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in beſides moſt ſoft beds they had nothing to comfort themſelues, in which they wallowed and ſlept till they ſnorted, ſome of the Schollers that were preſent at their departure being in a ſoberer conceite than the reſt, deſirous to ſée whither they would goe, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them faſt after, till they eſpied them on this durty eaſe, for in ſtead of beds they were all bewrapped, and ſome more than halfe ſunck in déepe &amp; yéelding mire by the riuers bancks. Whom when they ſaw in this more than miſerable caſe, moued with pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, conuayed them in Waggons home: and being demaunded in the morning (for then they were a litle wiſer) the occaſion of their ſo great and ſeldome ſéene diſorder, they declared it from the bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the ending, which they were ſo farre from beléeuing, that they counted it as canonicall, which when ſome Students reported vnto me, I could not abſtaine from hearty laughter, not onely to ſée how they had abuſed themſelues, but alſo others by ſo fond beliefe. For I ſaide that in drunkennes, ſo thicke a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour as riſeth from ſo thicke a matter as their Béere, clambering vp and ſpreading it ſelfe ſo vniuerſally in the fantaſie, maketh it conceaue no other impreſſion, but that which the minde afore it came to be ouerpreſſed was conuerſant about, and it was euident that in all the talke they had, there was nothinge mentioned but onely <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> merriments, and where a thing is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many ſo agréeingly talked off, it is likely it ſhould take effect aſwell in all as in one. Well, I was content to ſubſcribe to their folly rather to ſatisfie their ſelfe-willed conceites, than mine owne thoughte. Many odde prancks <hi>Fauſtus</hi> is made the father of, which are either ſo friuolous as no body can credite but like friuolous people, or ſo méerely ſmelling of the Caske, that a man may eaſily know the childe by the Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:178202:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>VVagners conference with Doctor Fauſtus, and how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably they broke vp their diſputations. CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVAGNER</hi> one morning aroſe betimes and departed to Wittenberg, but a ſmall mile from the houſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing puruayed himſelfe of al neceſſaries, was admitted for a ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler (immediately after his Maiſter was departed out of this World) into the Vniuerſity. Where, for that he was <hi>Fauſtus</hi> true and familiar ſeruaunt, he was both well and manifoldly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, wherein he remained in all ſolace amongeſt a greate number of his companions, who then rather frequented his company, not onely for that he was <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his ſeruaunt, whoſe memory was very freſhly continued among them, but that they were verely aſſured that he had a great part of his Maiſters skill and ſcience, which they honoured with more then lawfull reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
               <p>Vppon a day <hi>Chriſtopher Wagner</hi> (as manye times he did) ſeperated himſelfe from his other companions and frends, to ruminate vppon his melancholicke conceites, erring farre in a place full of Trées and the fulneſſe of Trées gaue it the name of a Groue, ſodainely like as all ſuch chaunces happe, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> or <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> Spirite clapt him vppon the ſhoulder, ſaying: <hi>VVagner,</hi> good morrowe. <hi>VVagner</hi> auayled his Schollers Bonnet, thinking verily that he was ſome other Student, but beholdinge his Maiſter <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> he was moſt terribly affrighted, and ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping aſide he began to mumble to himſelf a <hi>Benedicite,</hi> and croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelfe, rehearſing and ſaying <hi>CONIVRO TE IN NOMINE PATRIS ET FILII ET SPIRITVS SANCTI, &amp;c.</hi> making a Circle &amp;c. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> rowling his eyes and for méere fury and anger ſtamping bound (for ſo he ſéemed) with the vehemency of the Exorciſme ranne about moſt terribly the brimmes thereof, that therewith the neighbour ground did ſéeme to tremble, caſting out a blackiſh ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omy ſulphury ſmoake out of his mouth, wherwith the bright ayr was much darkned, at length appeaſed, either forced with neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or knauery, he ſpake and that very diſtinctly. <hi>VVagner</hi> (qd. he)
<pb facs="tcp:178202:8"/> art thou afeard of me as of a Spirite, or infernall Ghoſt, am not (I vngratefull raſcall) <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> am not I thy Maiſter <hi>Fauſtus?</hi> quoth <hi>VVagner</hi> very confidently, what thou wert I knowe, what alſo thou art who knowes not? though once my Maiſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow thou ſhalt be my ſeruaunt, though once my friend and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, now I may iuſtly tearm thée neither, the Lawes of Diuels hath not made me ſecure from thy tyranny, and howe may thy friendſhip auaile me? For how can that helpe which is not? affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are not amongeſt Féends, nor paſſions amongeſt Spirits. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Wherefore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> if thou wilt that I be thy Maiſter, as whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wilt or no, I will <hi>Coniure</hi> thée, &amp;c. to aunſwere directly and truely to all my queſtions.</q> 
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Ah <hi>VVagner</hi> (quoth <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) is this the duety of a ſeruaunt? doeſt thou miſtruſt, that in mee which neither I meane nor thou of honeſt thought and duetye oughteſt imagine? And as for affections in Spirites certainely there is none, but I am none, féele me my good <hi>VVagner,</hi> behold fleſh, bloud, and bones, and Spirites haue neither fleſh, bloude, nor bones. Beléeue me I ſhall teach thée the nature and eſſence of Diuels, I will teach thée that which neither thou canſt deſire of me or thinke <hi>Extra captum humanum.</hi> Then my good Boy <hi>VVagner</hi> come to me, and vſe me not as a Spirite whoſe bodye is nothing but a Spirit, and as Logicians ſay <hi>Subſtantia incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porea,</hi> and I will open vnto thée the ſecretes of the World, and Hell, and elſe whatſoeuer in the workes of Nature. Come my <hi>VVagner</hi> my ſonne, my darling, my ſwéete delight, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, the onely hope of my labours, boldly, louingly, curteouſlye aboue all, which am the very ſame matter and ſubſtaunce I once was, and if thou doubtſt as well thou maiſt reach thy hand to me, for I cannot mine to thée, and féele whether I am not as I ſay I am, fleſh, bloud, and bones:</q> 
                  <hi>VVagner</hi> halfe aſtoniſhed at this his feruent ſpéech, yet rather hearing it then beléeuing it: <q rend="margDblQuotes">Why <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> let me ſpeake to you ſomewhat more conſiderately, thou ſaieſt thou art ſubſtaunce, and all ſubſtaunce is heauy, and no heauy thing can aſcend vpwardes, and as thy conference with <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> doth plainely declare the place of Spirites is in the Aire, in which nothing that is heauy can remaine, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art not ſubſtaunce or not <hi>Fauſtus.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Quoth <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that no heauy thinges is in the Aire is plainely fals, for thou ſéeſt that
<pb facs="tcp:178202:8"/> materiall bodies are in the Aire, as haile, ſnowe and other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors:</q> 
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Whereto <hi>VVagner</hi> aunſwered: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> they truly are in the Aire not of the Aire, and you know the cauſes of them are terreſtrial vapors drawn from the earth by the attracttiue vertue of the Sunne, and therefore they fall downe becauſe they are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, for were they of the Aire as are Spirites, then ſhoulde they ſtill remaine in it, but briefly no violent motion may bee called naturall, as that heauy materiall Dew is carried from the earth by a violent and contrary motion: the Sunne therefore leauing the <hi>Zenyth</hi> of any <hi>Horiſon,</hi> and comming to the <hi>Nadir</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely the materiall bodies of Dew, (as the cauſes alwaies faile with the effectes) and nextly the concretion of Snow and Haile, becauſe they are ſubſtaunce, cannot remaine in the light and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heauy Aire: Wherefore I haue aunſwered thée that thou art ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Spirite or not ſubſtaunce.</q> I wondred when I read this diſcourſe, with what patience the Doctor could endure ſo long an argument, but it prooued otherwiſe, for the Doctor brake foorth into theſe ſpeaches vnable to containe himſelfe any longer.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                     <hi>Wagner</hi> thou ſéemeſt to gather naturall arguments of <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicall</hi> effectes, I ſay vnto thée <hi>Wagner</hi> ſith thou art thus far entred into a Philoſophicall diſcourſe, that I being as I am <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> may be, for ſo I am, a dweller in the profound <hi>Abyſſe</hi> of the Aire, whoſe compaſſe is meaſurable in this, that it is not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable: For let vs ſpeake according to men naturally the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fitte thy capacity, we ſée that in the regiment of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the man is of quality like to the predominant complexion and Element, as if Chollar abound, the man is light, nimble, and for a while furious, ſeldome ſtrong, ready to meddle, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with phanaticke illuſions: If Bloud abound hee is ruddy, faire, gentle, &amp;c. <hi>Et ſic de reliquis.</hi> If therefore the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Element is able ſo much to change the nature of man, as to make it aboue the reſt capable or incapable, the ſame reaſon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that this body of mine which thou ſéeſt, being gouerned and predomineirde by that quicke and ready ſpirite and ſoule which makes a man immortall is no hinderaunce why this corporal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of me ſhould accompany my ſpirite, not as a body, but as a parte of the ſame Spirite: and otherwiſe <hi>VVAGNER</hi> the whole world is in the Aire, and as it were the centre of the
<pb facs="tcp:178202:9"/> Heauens, and what ſubſtaunces ſoeuer is made, Fiſhes which dwell in the déepe Seas except (and yet not alwaies) are moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Air, <hi>Kit</hi> beléeue me I am as thou ſéeſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and the ſame very ſame.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVagner</hi> almoſt at the laſt caſt, ſayd, <q rend="margDblQuotes">we diſpute not what you are <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> but what by reaſon you may be.</q> 
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Well, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſéeing thou wilt not beléeue, nor giue any credite to my ſayings, and which I prooue by argumentes, I hope thou wilt beléeue thine owne eyes, and if thou ſéeſt what I ſaye vnto thée, thou wilt neither be obſtinate nor incredulous, and rather then <hi>VVagner</hi> (whome I doe loue as my ſelfe) ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with ſo palpable an Hereſie, beholde <hi>Wagner</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue,</q> and ſtreight waies he drewe his knife, the Prologue of his knauery, and looking firſt vppon <hi>Wagner,</hi> and next on the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon which he had in his hand, as if with his eies he woulde haue mooued him to ſome pitty, and mooued them to be witneſſes of the trueth, he ſtrake himſelfe into his thigh twiſe or thriſe, and after his ſtroakes followed bloud ſo haſtely, as if it woulde haue ouertaken the iniurious worker of his effuſion: which bloude <hi>Fauſtus</hi> receiued in a ſiluer Bowle, and ſtaunching his wound, but not vntill the bloud might be ſéene ouer the Cup brimmes, then <hi>Fauſtus</hi> lifted the bloude on high ſaying: <q rend="margDblQuotes">Sée here the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the trueth, <hi>Wagner</hi> take it, looke how freſhe it is, it is not that which comes from a Spirite, it is bloud both in nature and colour, and if this be not inough to make thée beléeue that which I doe tell thée, it bootes not, there is not any trueth at all.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I thought it enough for an extemporall <hi>Dis</hi> and controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, I thought the ſcholler had heard as well and as long as the Doctor had taught, but yet he had not ended. <hi>Wagner</hi> receyuing the Cuppe and looking on the bloud, beheld him without ſaying any thing, ſhewing by his ſilence his meaning. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to reuenge and recompence <hi>VVagner</hi> his vnbeliefe, <q rend="margDblQuotes">naye further (quoth he) féele my hand, tell me whether it hath not the naturall heate and eſſentiall ſolidity:</q> then immediatly he ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched foorth his arme. <hi>Wagner</hi> with ſodaine extaſie of ioy car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, ran to embrace his old Maiſter, as his newe friend, whome when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had excircled he fell to beating the poore
<pb facs="tcp:178202:9"/> Scholler moſt miſerably, that <hi>Wagners</hi> pittifull roaring, ſéemed to be an Eccho to the Doctors blowes, <q rend="margDblQuotes">now (quoth <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) hereafter be learned either to be more wary or leſſe miſtruſtfull,</q> and therewith laughing effuſedly vaniſhed away, leauing <hi>Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to be a witneſſe (yet almoſt halfe dead with his buffeting) of their conference, and that he was a good ſubſtantiall Burgeſſe of Hell: <hi>Wagner</hi> poore Boy for the ſpace of ſeauen houres not able ſcarce of himſelfe to ſturre or to take breath, and without much ſturring either of hand or foote, wherby any able life might be coniectured: At length lifting vppe his head and ſighing a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, (for a little was as much as he could doe at that time) he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe vp and laying his head vppon his hand and his hande vppon the ground, he after ſighs ſent out moſt ſorrowful grones, and after groanes ſome féeble wordes, as he after reported it to his companions and familiar acquaintaunce: to accuſe either his Maiſters rigour or his owne folly, he thought as méerely vain as little preuailing: Wherefore comforting himſelfe with his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, becauſe he was comfortleſſe, roſe vp, and looking for the cup of bloud (for the gaine of the ſiluer mooued him: In place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he found his Cap full of piſſe, and all beraied, ſore aſhamed and ſoare withall, ſo well as he might, which was ſorely inough, hée roſe vppe, and what by créeping and going he gotte whome to his Chamber, where hee abode till he had recouered his health again.</p>
               <p>Thus was his Philoſophicall incredulity recompenſed with ruſticall cruelty, ſuch was the good loue of the Spirite, that for a long ſpace after he was not able to walke out of his Chamber. This did he affirme for moſt certaine truth, and to his ſaying ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his beaten skin, a teſtimoniall and witneſſe to his familiarly beloued acquaintaunce, one of the which recounted it all ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in a Letter from Wittenberg to me, where I was at Lypt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zip, knowing that I intended to certifie my friendes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of a matter ſo notable and ſtraunge, and worthy of memory, and augmented by Fame more then of very déed, for the idle hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fellowes hauing gotten ſuch a notable fellow as <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to Father their lies vppon, ceaſed not daily and hourely to begette new children, but they coſt very litle nurſing and bringing vppe, they had the wide Worlde, a very good Grandam where they
<pb facs="tcp:178202:10"/> might féede their fill: As for the diſputations betwixt thoſe two in this place, and thoſe which you ſhall finde in other places like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe aboundantly, conſider from whoſe braines they procéede, for you muſt giue the Germane leaue to ſhew his Art, for witte for the moſt part they haue very little, but that which they toile for like Cart Horſes. But in all their doings you ſhall eaſelye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue if any thing be in them excellent, either with how much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and vrging they bring it foorth, or howe it is wetted ouer with dropping of the Tappe excéedingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Wagners cooſenage committed vppon the ſellers of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters goodes. CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <p>ACcording to the Lawe of the countrey the goods of <hi>Fauſtus</hi> were to bee confiſcate and applied to the Treaſury, by an Edict publiſhed againſt Coniurers by <hi>Sigiſmunde</hi> Duke of Saxony. According ta the tenour thereof <hi>Fauſtus</hi> goods were to be alienated, but <hi>Wagner</hi> ſo handled the matter that the ſpeare being ſtucke vp, and his goods ſet to be ſold, <hi>Wagner</hi> had prouided bidders and money of his owne, the one were ſuch as neuer were ſéene more, and the other but round counters.</p>
               <p>The Meſſengers being thus cooſened by <hi>Wagner,</hi> durſt not for ſhame report it, nor he for feare of further puniſhment vaunt of it: the one contented to put vp the loſſe quietly, and the other to enioy them without further contradiction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The deſcription of Vienna. CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>FAme had ſo farre carried the report of <hi>Fauſtus</hi> death, as it had the memory of his life, and for by continuall motion rumours encreaſe, as ſaieth the Heroicall fountaine of Latine verſe <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil.</hi>
               </p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Nobilitate viget vireſque acquirit eundo.</q>
               <p>In Auſtrich theſe newes were very frequent, beeing a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince
<pb facs="tcp:178202:10"/> mightely repleniſhed with people, and marching vpon the hems of the Hungarian, is a neare neighbour to the moſt cruell Dog and tyraunt the Turke. In Vienna, a Citty of the ſame by which as the Thames by London the great, and often but neuer inough prayſed Riuer of great Danuby kéepes his current the Citty it ſelfe (beeing euery way bigger then the faire Cittye of London) within the Walles, the head of the Citty reſteth vppon the mountain of Orſtkirken, the front diſplayeth the wide plains vppon the diſcendent of the ſame Hill, but ſhée waſhes her féet in the Riuer: her body and her breſt couering the large valley ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betwixt Hill and Hil, not farre into the Citty the Danuby is deriued into two armes, which by running about a certaine Hil, of ſome halfe mile and more, méete at length againe in the ſame Channell: In this Iland is the Dukes Court, out of which are two and thirty maruailous goodly ſtone Bridges, intending to either ſide of the Citty: at the very promontories ends, ſtandes two no leſſe faire, then high and ſtrong Caſtles, in this place did the Duke kéepe his Court, with very great royalty, vnto whom when this was reported, hearing of a certaine that <hi>Wagner</hi> had great ſtore of his maiſters skill and whatſoeuer, hee cauſed one that in ſuch matters is commonly commaunded, to ride to <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg,</hi> to the intent to heare the trueth, for many things more then the trueth were certified vnto him: the meſſenger without delay (becauſe the iourney was long) departed and left the Court, and we him a while.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>A long diſcourſe betwixt the Diuell and VVagner, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a good Philoſophicall repaſt. CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVAgner</hi> ſolitary muſing in his Chamber and conuerſing with many multitudes of thoughtes, ſodainely appeared <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> his maſters Familiar, after him <hi>Akercocke,</hi> which was <hi>VVagners,</hi> and after all <hi>Fauſtus:</hi> Quoth <hi>Mepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophiles</hi> what cheare? Sirrha ſuch as you ſée, we are as wee were and neuer the better: and welcome <hi>Akercocke,</hi> but my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> that you come at this time I reioyce. So then
<pb facs="tcp:178202:11"/> they all ſate downe, and ſate right againſt him. Then entred in diuerſe delicate viands, and there not then to be ended with vnſéen <hi>Symphonies</hi> of Muſiike. Then ſpake <hi>Wagner</hi> and ſayd <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diteiam riuos,</hi> now we haue ſatisfied our appetite with meate, I pray you heare me with patience, for I haue a thing in my minde of which I would faine be reſolued, but becauſe you ſo fowly, and ſo often fowly entreated my Maiſter, for demaunding ſome que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, you ſhall ratifie this Article with me againe. <hi>1. That in my demaunds you ſhall aunſwer truly and patientiy,</hi> for what hurt can redound to you by aunſwering of a queſtion, ſéeing if you are ſure of any thing you may hold faſt, a queſtion cannot take it away: Without delaye theſe good fellowes confirmed the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle with a great oath: but he would take their ſimple word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſurety he knew their honeſty ſo well. Then <hi>VVagner</hi> pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe his Cap into his eies, and leaning vppon his elbow a while, and throwing vp his eies to Heauen, and then ſighing, at length folding his armes within themſelues, ſate ſtill a litle time, then ſpitting a little and fetching a hearty hem with a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſpake vnto them thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Sirs, it is not vnknown vnto you how deare I haue alwayes accounted of my Maiſter, whoſe condition is as farre from that it was as mine from yours, for which I haue more often lamented his departure then mine owne miſery, beeing once euery waye a man, ſo throughly inſtructed with the weapons of all Sciences, that in all the world hardly his péere could be found, ſo that your victory ouer ſuch a man is more to be wailed then euer manye a thouſand ſuch as I am. To be ſhort that you may vnderſtand whither I will goe without further Oration. Wherefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you, I pray you, nay I by your Article commaund you, that you declare vnto me truely without colluſion, whither that <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> here preſent in that ſtate wherein he now is, may come again to be a liuing man amongeſt vs, either his olde ſhape renewed, or he in a new: For ſome Philoſophers ſay, and ſome Diuines, as <hi>Origines</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and whither they ſay truely or no I know not, that no ſooner the ſoule of man departeth from one but that it doth enter into another. Wherefore I conſidering with my ſelfe thus much, and often for his cauſe that he may not onely be <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> but alſo a liuing man and dweller vppon the earth,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:11"/> to enioy not onely thoſe graces which through his great deſarts he had loſt, but alſo according to his infinit knowledge, multiply them through Gods fauors againe and again aboundantly. And though you ſhall perhaps deny that the ſame Indiuiduall cannot be againe ſo reſuſcitated, yet that <hi>Numero</hi> it may in ſpite of you al, I kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> may: for we do not doubt that the ſame Indiuidual may <hi>Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ro</hi> be againe regotten, becauſe that after ſeauen and thirty thouſand yeares, the heauenly conſtellation ſhall be in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point <hi>per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the ſame then that now it is, according to <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> and the Aſtronomers. And therfore we ſhal be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero,</hi> and ſhall ſit in this or that ſchoole or place as now we doe, that is in that <hi>Magno anno,</hi> in that great yeare: Whereuppon <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid, that after the great yeare he ſhould return to <hi>Athens,</hi> and ſhould there read: Becauſe the conſtellation ſhall happen ſo, therefore that returning, the ſame effects ſhal with them likewiſe return. Now hauing heard my reſolution, anſwer me to my firſt propoſition in ful &amp; amply, as that I may be ſatisfied.</q> At the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this ſpéech <hi>Fa.</hi> turnd his head aſide laying it betwixt his hands hiding it, ſo ſat a great while. <hi>Ake.</hi> he friskt vp &amp; down for he had neither clog nor chain, becauſe he was in the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the wild ones, and ouer the table and backe again. <hi>Ak.</hi> was the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar which <hi>F.</hi> gaue to <hi>W.</hi> who asked him in the faſhion of an Ape. Such cranks, ſuch lifts, caréers and gambalds, as he plaid there, would haue made a horſe laugh. <hi>Meph.</hi> who as it ſemed was the ſpeaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Parliament in hel, roſe &amp; walked about very haſtely, at length he came to the table and ſtriking his fiſt on it (the print was ſéene <hi>2.</hi> yeare after, and was carried to <hi>S. Margets</hi> church for a relique, to ſhew what a hot fellow the diuell is in his anger) and again beating ſaid, thou, and then left, and came and went, &amp; came and went again, here he takes me one booke and hurls it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Cupboorde, and then he takes the Cupboord and hurls it againſt the wall, and then he takes the wall and throwes it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the houſe, and the houſe out at the Window. Pacifying his rage at the length, rowling his eyes, and ſéeming beate his téeth together, ſate down further off, and thus quietly ſpake with a lowde voice. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Were it not <hi>VVagner</hi> that our ſolemne vow, forbiddeth to diſturbe or torment thée for any demandes, this thy fond pride ſhuld be rewarded with moſt intollerable puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts:
<pb facs="tcp:178202:12"/> As for the queſtion I wil anſwer thée more ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tially then ſuch a fooliſh doltiſh one doth require. And for that we haue day inough before vs I wil trauail further in it then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grauity of the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t can require, if it be but that thou maieſt ſée how great an Aſſe thou art, which canſt imagine ſo groſſe a matter in thy more groſſe head: As for thy great Péere be it as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to expect it you, in the meane we will enioy him and thée at our pleaſure in deſpite of God and Heauen and all his imperiall armies of ſaints. Thy queſtion is this: <hi>Whither the Spirite of a damned man can returne into the body of another man.</hi> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Negatiuely, it cannot.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                     <hi>1</hi> If this were to them graunted, then they ſhould obſerue and kéepe the <hi>Embrious</hi> in the Wombe of the mother, that they might conſtitutiuely vnite themſelues to it, to haue at the leaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſenſuall conſolation, and delectation.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Then ſecondly becauſe it is common to reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to faſhion and informate the body, and to perfect it with ſome natural delightment, not to vexe it.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Then thirdly becauſe of the law and order of Nature, the ſoules from the places in their departure to them allotted, aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and deputed of God, neither doe nor can depart at any time: for it is written: For the ſoule is a Spirite going and returning. And they which doe otherwiſe hold opinion are to be accuſed, nay condemned in this with <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> who did abſtaine from all liuing <hi>Animals</hi> and creatures, beléeuing that in ſome the ſoules of ſome men did dwell and abide. Thus farre the <hi>Arrogonian</hi> named <hi>Bartholomew Sybilla</hi> a <hi>Monopolitane,</hi> who writ vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this queſtion being at Wittenberg, at the requeſt of him that did ſet forth the Dutch Coppy ſhew himſelfe, to be a good Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher and no worſe Diuine. But marke what followes, this is written according to men in faith: the Diuell was out of the firſt ſtréete of Coany when he was paſt this laſt period. For that <hi>Pythagorical</hi> opinion, if that were: this abſurdity would follow: (I will ſpeake plainely the rather to fitte thy capacity) and if the ſoule ſhould paſſe out of the dead into the liuing, then ſhould mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality be the cauſe of the ſoules immortality (this is pretily ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) and by that meanes make it corruptible, which cannot be. And ſéeſt thou <hi>Wagner?</hi> for I will teach thée by demonſtrations,</q> and
<pb facs="tcp:178202:12"/> therwith he tooke a coal of fire, &amp; held it to him ſo long that it came to be but a coale, <q rend="margDblQuotes">now thou ſéeſt <hi>Wagner,</hi> that ſo long as fire was in this ſubiect it had life, but the quality being remoued from the quantity, neither is the quality found or ſéene or known whither it vaniſheth, nor can the ſame fire though fire may return into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother body or ſubiect albeit the quantity remaineth. Thus may the ſoule of man be compared to the fire in the coal, as concerning his entraunce and departure, but not réentrance, for that coale may take life againe, that is fire, but ſo cannot humane body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one ſpirit can be vnited but to one body, and not two to one, nor one ſpirite to two bodies: Wherefore that ſpirite being depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it is irreuocable becauſe of the vnity, and the impoſſibility of returning in the one, in the other of receiuing any other. As for other reaſons directly by circumſtaunce, if the Soule goeth either to ioy or paine immediatly, then I am certaine that that hope which thou haſt is ſo méerly vaine, as any thing which may hap vnder that title: For proofe behold,</q> and then through the Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot doore of <hi>VVagners</hi> ſtudy entred in two Kings, which draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſwords did there in preſence combate together fiercely &amp; couragioſly, one of them ſhortly after fainting vnder the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſtroakes fell downe, the other victorious, yet wounded, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry canonically as a man may ſay, ſtaggerd immediatly, as if hée would faine haue not fallen, yet for all that he fell: then entred two men carrying Torches with the ſnuffes downwards, with great ſolemnity (more then is here néedfull to bee recapitulated, for I ſée nothing but that this might haue béene very well left out for any thing worthy the grauity of the matter) which when they had carried out the firſt ſlaine combattant, with armed men, and a dying ſtroake of the Drum, clothed all in the colour which beſt notes by his external hew, the internall ſorrow: Then next there entred two Pages all in ſiluer white crownd with Baies, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Torches aloft declaring the height of their glory by the height of their flames: next to them diuerſe Trumpetters and all in white, vrging forth into the waſt aire their victorious floriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, next a great ſtandard bearer, and I cannot tell what, but the concluſion was, that the triumph was excéeding great and pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous, adorned with as many ceremonies as ſuch a victory might or could be, the Spirite when they were all gone began to ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:178202:13"/> and ſayd, this was the battaile which was fought for the greate Realme of Aſia, by <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Orontides,</hi> where <hi>Orontides</hi> was ſlaine, and <hi>Hercules</hi> ſore wounded, but yet recouered after which he atchieued his <hi>12</hi> labors, &amp; the <hi>13</hi> of which the Poet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the hardeſt of al.
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Tertius hinc decimus labor eſt duriſsimns, vna</l>
                     <l>Quinquaginta ſimul ſtuprauit nocte puellas.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This Hiſtory is as I doe thinke in the Chronicle of Hel, for I did neuer heare of it before, nor any body elſe, I appeale to all the Hiſtories. Marry it may be this was when <hi>Hercules</hi> was a little Boy, and then peraduenture in déede the recordes make no mention of it, but yet we haue that recorded which he did whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was leſſe then a little Boy, as his killing of a Serpent in his Craddle, and ſuch a Hiſtory as I do remember is enrould in the golden Booke of the ſeauen wiſe Maiſters of Roome, an autenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call author. But let that paſſe and let vs draw more neare vnto the cauſe: For as the diuell was afore our daies, ſo by authority he may alledge experience, and we muſt of neceſſity beléeue that it is either true or a lie. <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> continued his ſpéech for all this Aparentheſis, declaring <hi>VVagner</hi> his meaning in this point, for (quoth he) <q rend="margDblQuotes">as you ſe theſe two champions contending for the title of victory, one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt néeds if they try the extreameſt as they did receiue the diſhonor, the other the glory, ſo in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat wherein the dying body battaileth with the liuely ſoule, the ſoule if grace hath made acceptable ſhall enioy thoſe euerlaſtinge pleaſures of Paradiſe, and dwell in heauen bleſſed and glorious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the beautifull Angels, but if it be counted as reprobate &amp; outcaſt of God, then according to that puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which his great ſins did deſerue, he can haue no other place but the continuall hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of hell, wherein we miſerable dwell, and the vgly company of black diuels and his frightfull Angels. There is no other meane but honor or diſhonor in this caſe, no other meane but ioy or pain, no other meane but heauen or hell perpetually: there is no place left for a third. I could more copiouſly diſpute of this matter, but that I wil not be too tedious in ſo exile a queſtion. For where it is ſaid in an author to which I am witnes, for I ſtoode by his elbow when he writ the lines. <hi>Animae ſunt in loco certo &amp; expectant iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſe inde poſſunt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mouere.</hi> Which place as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the precedent chapter is heauen or hell: again it is ſayd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima
<pb facs="tcp:178202:13"/> quae pecauerit ipſa morietur.</hi> Of neceſſity then the ſoule to whom the Lord imputeth not his ſin ſhall liue, for they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for the ſoule that is in ioy wil not come to theſe troubles, nor that which is in torment cannot: therefore it is ſaid: <hi>Et reuertatur puluis in terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quemadmodum erat, &amp; ſpiritus reuertatur ad Dominum qui dedit illum,</hi> ſo there is no mention in any ſcripture of the ſoules returning, but to a certain place de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of God to him.</q> But before I goe any further in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> declaring of that which is here to be ſet down, I know they that haue their conſciences more of the preciſe cut, will ſay, that there was a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diuell, true it is he is learned, ſtrong, and aboue all humaine conceit, ſubtill and crafty: and if they ſay it is blaſphemouſly done to haue the word ſpoken to the world by ſo vile a mouth, firſt they know how mightely the diuell is conuerſant in holy writ, in any thing to ouerthrow a chriſtian thought, knowing that as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God is a word of power to attaine ſaluation to whom grace is giuen: and to worke eternall damnation where that gift is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, knowing it is the onely meanes to debell and conquere the chriſtian thought, for as a man is gouerned by a law &amp; by it liues, ſo if any thing be euidently directed againſt him in it, it ſlayes his hart, it ouerthrowes him, it takes away his power for euer, nor is it more blaſphemous to be ſpeake to vs men, then to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as it is in <hi>S. Alathero,</hi> where the diuell was not afeard, to aſſayle his creatour with moſt terrible argumentes of the diuine letter. They which haue right mindes can perſwade themſelues accordingly: but otherwiſe they may cauill as long as they will, which they may do to their ſmall profit, aſſuring them this that in coueting by fault finding to ſéeme learned, they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the notes and reproach not only of the learned, but euen of the abſurd and barbarous rude fooles, and that they are the onelye ſpirits of error &amp; contention, and the chiefe cauſes of vnbeliefe by vayn reaſonings and queſtions to the vnreſolued chriſtian. But as for this ſpéech which is but <hi>Humile dicendigenus</hi> in very truth, let them thus thinke, that if there were any ſuch controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betwixt <hi>VVagner</hi> and his ſpirit, as is here mentioned, that thoſe are not the words which were ſpoken, but that they doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede from a yong Scholler who gaue me this coppy, and not of a diuell, of whoſe familiarity &amp; frequency &amp; of other circumſtantiue
<pb facs="tcp:178202:14"/> cauſes, I will God willing in the <hi>Cataſtraphe</hi> and concluſion of this Booke deliuer vnto you my poore opinion. In the mean while I will follow the matter into which we are fallen my good frends &amp; without further adoe I pray without any more excuſiue phraſe, patiently expect the good houre wherein the death of this volume is prepared: <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> taking breath a little, preſented his ſpéech ſaying: <q rend="margDblQuotes">it is ſaid likewiſe. <hi>Factum eſt autem vt more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur mendicus. &amp;c. And it came to paſſe that the begger dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and was carried away of Angels into Abrahams boſome, and that rich man died and was buried, and he being in Hel lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp his eies, when he was in torments, and ſaw Abraham a farre off and Lazarus in his boſome.</hi>
                  </q> Nor nothing doth that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne which is ſaid of the Papiſt, that he cannot come into Gods preſence nor be one of the elect vnleſſe they be purified from their ſins, for which purification, they ordain a place ſo terribly ſtucke with pins, néedles, daggers, ſwords, nailes, &amp;c. ſo ſoultring with hote burning ſurnaces, and ſo euery way formidable with mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall ſulphury fires, that no tongue can expreſſe, nor any heart i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, wherein the ſinfull ſoule muſt be many times and often clenſed, but I hope if this were true then <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhould haue bin likewiſe ſo dreſt in their terrible imagined terrors, which he was not, vnleſſe they will be ſo impudent to ſay that he had no ſinne. I ſhall not néede to diſpute how abſurd it is to ſay that the ſin of the ſoule in the body committed, muſt be extirpated and purified by a materiall ſubſtaunce and rigour, nor of the matter of the like ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. And hereupon he ſemed to ſigh as if ſome ſodain thought had ouerpreſt his ſtomacke. I can quoth he largely diſcourſe of al diuine and humaine propoſitions, but as the vnlearned Parrat who ſpeaketh oft and much, and vnderſtandeth neuer any thing to profite himſelfe. Ah that vnto vs Spirites no ſecrets are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, no doings of man vnhid, and yet wee Diuels curſed of God are incapable of any of Gods mercies, though through them we were created. We know repentance is the way to attaine the celeſtiall ſauour: we know Gods mercies how great they are, &amp; that we ought to diſpaire of nothing, yet there is nothing (ſuch is our ſéeing blindneſſe) ſo it appertaine to God and godlineſſe, of which we doe not diſpaire. No <hi>Wagner</hi> wee are ſo farre from li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing againe, as we are from certainty to bee ſaued. <q rend="margDblQuotes">But in ſtead
<pb facs="tcp:178202:14"/> of that we are croſſed with all kinde of vexation, for ſince the firſt time that I with my Maiſter and fellowes fell downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen being of the moſt royall order of Angels, Poteſtates, Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, and Seraphins, riding vppon the winges of the Winde in all bright ſhining Maieſty, and enioying the moſt glorious and uiuine preſence of our Creatour, till for our heart ſwelling pride, and hawty inſolency, within as little ſpace of time as wee were created in, with his dreadful lightning threw vs downe headlong into the bottomleſſe <hi>Abyſſes</hi> of the Aire, wherein wee endure theſe tortures and like wicked ſouls with vs, as our manifold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts haue brought vppon vs. And for that we know that the way to mercy is vtterly denied, and that we are as much hated of our ſelues as of God, we thinke it the ſwéeteſt remedy in theſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde miſeries to haue partakers of our common woe with vs. Wherefore it is moſt expedient for vs to be thus enuiouſly maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous againſt all mankind, making them too as far in Gods dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full curſe as our ſelues.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVagner</hi> melting at theſe words, his eies vndid the great burthen of his ſorrow, ſtrayning himſelfe ſo long that he wept, &amp; yet could ſay nothing, but onely a ſmall volley of ſobs haſtily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> ſéeing how <hi>VVagner</hi> was drowned in ſo déepe a melancholy, told him pulling him by the ſléeue that he would be ſtill demaunding of ſuch fooliſh queſtions which will profite him ſo little as mought be. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Knoweſt thou not (quoth he) that all the Rhetorickes are the ſeruaunts of my tongue, or that we can moue pitty or hatred when we pleaſe, foole as thou art forget theſe vaine conferences, perſwade thy ſelfe that they are but the effect of ſpeach, long canſt thou not liue, and yet doeſt thou liue as if thou didſt not long: youthly ſhould be thy thoughts, and fraught with the ranck luſtines of conceite and amorous delight, if thou wilt aske queſtions let them be ſuch as appertaine to loue and wealth, to pleaſure, to paſtime, and to merriment. Howe ſaieſt thou to ſuch a one, naming a Gentlewoman the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Lady vnder the cope of Heauen? thou ſhalt enioy her, nay any one ſo ſhe be one whome thou liſts to call beautifull, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thy eies ſhall lay their delight vppon. And preſently Muſick was hearde ſo ſwéete, ſo plenteous, and ſo rauiſhinge, as if on Muſicke depended all ſwéete, all plenty, al rauiſhment.</q> The doors
<pb facs="tcp:178202:15"/> conuaying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues aſide, as giuing place to ſo diuine a fairenes, entring in a blew Veluet Gowne raſed, and thickely beſet in the gards with moſt pure Doches of gould, not altogether ignorant of precious ſtones, ſued with royall Ermines, looſe about her: her heads ornament, (though greater ornament to her head then her head there could not be) was a kind of atirde Caule (ſuch as I haue ſéene none in England according to their deſcription) raiſed vp at the corners with ſtiffe ſquare wiers of beaten gould, on that a Chaplet or frontire of Roſes, on the Chaplet a vaile of Lawne, which couered all her faire body denying the ſight of ſuch an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, but onely through a ſhadow: In briefe ſhée was ſuch a one as would haue rouſed the baſeſt deſire in the whole Worlde to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt wondrous enterpriſes, in her hands ſilken ſoft, ſhée helde a Lute, diſcourſing ſwéetelye vppon the ſolemn ſtringes with her nimble fingers. A maide carrying a blew waxen Taper in a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer white Candleſticke made in faſhion of a Cenſor, but it was deriued into two ſeuerall branches, in whoſe ends were curiouſly wroght two moſt beautiful places to pight tapers one. The maid bir Lady would haue well contented a reaſonable proper Squire, it was a pretty rancke laſſe, round about as plump as a Bladder, which being yet ſmoaking new is blowen vp with Winde: well I will not trouble you with theſe rude deſcriptions any longer, but deſire you to conceaue the excellency of this fair Lady, for it is farre more copious in the Dutch Coppy then is here neceſſary to to be recapitulated. <hi>Wagners</hi> heart leaping at this ſight looked about him, as if he would haue no body priuy to himſelfe but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſo it was in déede, for <hi>Fauſtus, Mephoſtophiles,</hi> and <hi>Akercocke</hi> were gone, and thereupon with a boone courage ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing himſelfe vppon his toes, and wéeding himſelfe in the beſt Germane faſhion, as he could very well, began to trauaile vnto her, but remembring his bad apparell ſtept backe and bluſht, and hid his face, but ſodainely retourning againe as if he had known now how rather to become his wéedes, began to fewter himſelfe, but O wonder, his habite was changed with his thought, and he was now no more <hi>Wagner</hi> but <hi>Armiſuerio</hi> the Ladies Lorde. And to be ſhort this new <hi>Armiſuerio</hi> and old <hi>VVagner</hi> mette with the Lady, and ſaluting her in the beſt kinde of <hi>Bon noche,</hi> vſed her as he would doe his Lady, and ſhée him as her Lord. So
<pb facs="tcp:178202:15"/> paſſing auer their weary night in ſuch pleaſure as I could find in my heart to enioy or any man (vnleſſe an Euenuch beſide.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The arriual of the Meſſenger at Wittenberg, and the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of VVagner. CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>IT is time to winde about another furrow with our ſwerting Téeme and bring our ſpéech to another matter, entring out of one into another, for change is ſwéet. Not forgetting by the way the Purceuant or as we may better call him a Meſſenger who lately departed from Vienna in Auſtria, and I thinke by that time this diſputation was finiſhed, had almoſt ouertaken all the way betwixt him and home, which was ſome fiftéene daies tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, after fiue Germane miles to the daies labour, and arriued at Wittenberg, by enquiry came to <hi>Wagners</hi> chamber, which was in the way as yée goe to the Publicke Schooles, as yée goe from <hi>Melancthons</hi> houſe, a pretty houſe &amp; of a reaſonable large ſiſe built of hewen ſtone, and enuironed with a good thicke Wall, of ſome thrée foote and a halfe thicke and twenty high, at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome guarded about with a good broad Mount of ſeuen yardes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and round about very large and ſecret walkes, farre from al company and reſort, and there he might talke without feare with the Diuel and his Dam to, thither this fellow comming knocked peremptorily at the doore, <hi>Wagner</hi> was euen now gone to his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; riſing vp in a Pedlers chafe, that he ſhould goe to his booke, eſpecially if it were goodneſſe not once in a moneth, and yet then to be troubled, he ſwore a litle thing would make him neuer ſtudy more, it ſhould not, but putting one his cloake and his hat, came downe and vnbolted the doore: Vnto whome the Meſſenger ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a pretty iolly fellow did ſome little of reuerence, <hi>Wagner</hi> as yet ſcarce hauing let downe his choller, ſtept backe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing him weare ſuch a Wéede as Serieants there doe vſe to weare, thinking with himſelfe that ſome had come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prince for cooſening of his ſeruaunts, ſhut the doore vppon him and went powting and ſwearing and pittifully chafing, that if the knaue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſue him he would ſurely kill him at the leaſt, downe hee fetcht a good Baſtinado and ſet it behind the doore and opened it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and demaunded ſomewhat mildly what he had to ſay vnto
<pb facs="tcp:178202:16"/> him, to whom the Meſſenger ſayd, that he came from the Arch-Duke of Auſtria from Vienna, who willing to heare ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety of his Maiſter, did ſend for him aſſuring himſelfe, that not onely he could ſatisfie his deſire in that matter, but alſo ſhew him as much skill as euer his maiſter had. <hi>Wagner</hi> hearing the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of his meſſage with good effectual words, thankt him agayn, and rendred moſt ſeruiceable reuerence to his good Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for remembring ſo gently of his poore ſeruant &amp;c. Deſiring him to tarry vntill he might ſet euery thing in due order and hee would not faile to goe with him. The Meſſenger did not denye him, and ſo they went vp together into their Chamber, whome euer after the Meſſenger loued dearly for his proper behauior and perſonage, for in déede <hi>Wagner</hi> was a very goodly young man, being about the common ſtature, ſtreight and reaſonably ſlender, well truſt, his haire very yellow and his face faire, his bearde which did but now expreſſe the bloſſomes of his luſty courage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like yellow, wel mannered, as hauing bin brought vp amongſt the fineſt and beſt ſort of Diuels: hauing a pleaſant filed tong, and would make the dainty Rhetoricke come as ſmoothly out of his mouth as an arrow out of a péece of paper, well could he talke of amorous deuices, &amp; entreat the braueſt Ladies with ſwéet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, in truth by report he was a Gentle-like man, and accompliſhed with as many fine partes as a better man than hee might iuſtly vaunt of: he could play vppon any fine Inſtrument, and was not ignorant of any laudable exerciſes, carrying a braue luſty conceite euen to his death: and furniſhed with many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions of art, ther was nothing wanting in the man but a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>The Tragedy of Doctor Fauſtus ſeene in the Ayre, and acted in the preſence of a thouſand people of Wittenberg. An. 1540. CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>IN a braue ſommer Sun-ſhine day, the whole people of Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg being gathered together, to beholde certaine matches for the Garland who could drinke moſt, and alſo to ſée a match ſhotte at a pair of Buts with Harquebuſhiers, as their order is in a low meddow hard by the Elue: which now being on his freſheſt pride
<pb facs="tcp:178202:16"/> was full of fine and ſwéete flowers, being in the latter end of the moneth wherein the Sunne departs from the laſt embracings of <hi>Gemini.</hi> On a ſodaine there was ſéene a maruailous bright and glorious Rayne-bow, ſpreading the wide armes ouer the wide World, and ſtreight was there hard a noiſe of Trumpets, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge a ſhort floriſh, and then another, and by and by another all alike ſhort, at the which the aſſembly was wonderouſly affeard, and liſtned, deſirous to ſée the effect of this wonder and ſtraunge miracle, ſome of them fell to their <hi>Aue maries</hi> luſtely, thinkinge that the vniuerſall Doome had béene at that inſtant, as thus they beheld with admiration, they might diſtinctly perceiue a goodlye Stage to be reard (ſhining to ſight like the bright burniſh golde) vppon many a faire Pillar of cleareſt Criſtall, whoſe féete reſted vppon the Arch of the broad Rayne-bow, therein was the high Throne wherein the King ſhould ſit, and that prowdly placed with two and twenty degrées to the top, and round about curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wrought chaires for diuerſe other Potentates, there might you ſée the ground-worke at the one end of the Stage whereout the perſonated diuels ſhould enter in their fiery ornaments, made like the broad wide mouth of an huge Dragon, which with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall armies of ſmoake and flame breathed foorth his angry ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes rage, round about the eies grew haires not ſo horrible as men call briſſels, but more horrible as long and ſtiffe ſpeares, the téeth of this Hels mouth far out ſtretching, and ſuch as a man might well call monſtrous, and more then a man can by wordes ſignifie: to be ſhort his hew of that colour which to himſelf means ſorrow, &amp; to others miniſters like paſſion: a thicke lampe blacke, blacker then any paint, any Hell, blacker then it owne ſelfe. At the other end in oppoſition was ſéene the place wherein the bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe skirmiſhes are ſo often perfourmed on the Stage, the Wals (not ſo pleaſaunt as old wiues woulde haue their tales addorned with) of Paſty cruſt, but Iron attempered with the moſte firme ſtéele, which being brightly filed ſhone as beautifully ouer the whole place as the Pale ſhiminge Cynthia, enuironed with high and ſtately Turrets of the like mettall and beautye; and hereat many in gates and out-gates: out of each ſide lay the ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Ordinaunce, ſhewing at their wide hollowes the crueltye of death: out of ſundry loopes many large Banners and Streamers
<pb facs="tcp:178202:17"/> were pendant, brieflye nothing was there wanting that might make it a faire Caſtle. There might you ſée to be ſhort the Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, the Poſts, the Ladders, the tiring houſe, there euery thing which in the like houſes either vſe or neceſſity makes common. Now aboue all was there the gay Clowdes <hi>Vſque quaque</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with the heauenly firmament, and oftenſpotted with gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den teares which men call Stars: There was liuely portrayed the whole Imperiall Army of the faire heauenly inhabitauntes, the bright Angels, and ſuch whoſe names to declare in ſo vile a matter were too impious and ſacrilegious. They were ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally done that you would haue ſworne it had béene Heauen it ſelf or the Epitome of it, or ſome ſecond Heauen, and a new Heauen it was, from thence like dewy drops wherein the Sun layes his golden ſhine, making them to appeare like ſmall golden teares, the ſwéete odours and comforting liquor ſtreamde, and ſéemde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to raine from thence but they neuer fell, but kept a beaten path from downe on high wherein the deſcending Angell might reioyce. I ſhould be too long if I ſhould expreſſe this rare Stage, eſpecially in ſuch ſort and ſuch like words as the like occaſion in a more worthy ſubiect wuld require, but of neceſſity we muſt bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply our deſcriptions to the nature of the whole Hiſtory. Wee muſt not faile in the firſt principle of Art, according to that of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race.</hi>
               </p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Humano capiti ceruicem pictor equinam</l>
                  <l>Iungere ſi velit, &amp; varias inducere plumas</l>
                  <l>Vndique collatis membris, vt turpiter atrum</l>
                  <l>Deſinat in piſcem mulier formoſa ſuperne:</l>
                  <l>Spectatum admiſsi riſum teneatis amici.</l>
                  <l>Credit e Piſones iſti fabulae fore librum</l>
                  <l>Per ſimilem.</l>
                  <l>Non vt placidis cocant immitia.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I ſhall not néede to turne backe to declare the déepe aſtoniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people, who are alwaies in moſt ſmall manners in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced eaſely to wondering, but now this excellent faire Theator erected, immediatly after the third ſound of the Trumpets, there entreth in the Prologue atttired in a blacke veſture, and making his thrée obeyſances, began to ſhew the argument of that Sceni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Tragedy, but becauſe it was ſo far off they could not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:178202:17"/> the wordes, and hauing thrice bowed himſelfe to the high Throne, preſently vaniſhed. Then out of this repreſentaunce of Hels mouth, iſſued out whole Armies of fiery flames, and moſte thick foggy ſmoakes, after which entred in a great batell of foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Diuels, all armed after the beſt faſhion with pike &amp;c, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the ſtroake of the couragious Drum, who girded about laid ſiege to this faire Caſtle, on whoſe Wals after the ſummons <hi>Fauſtus</hi> preſented himſelfe vppon the battelments, armed with a great number of Croſſes, pen and incke hornes, charmes, chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, ſeales; periapts &amp;c. who after ſharpe wordes defled the whole aſſembly, ſéeming to ſpeake earneſtly in his owne defence, and as they were ready to reare the Ladders, and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hadde begun to prepare for the counterbattery, determining to throw downe vppon the aſſemblies heads ſo many heauy charmes and coniurations, that they ſhould fall downe halfe way from the aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cendant, whilſt theſe things began to waxe whot from the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd Heauen, there deſcended a Legion of bright Angels ridinge vppon milke white Chariots, drawn with the like white ſtéeds, who with celeſtiall diuine melody came into the Towre, to the intent to fight for the Doctor againſt his furious enemies, but he wanting pay-money, and voide in déede of all good thoughts not able to abide their moſt bleſſed preſence ſent them away, and they returned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they came, ſorrowfully lamenting his moſt wilfull obſtinacy, whilſt he had all be nointed the Wals with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Water, and painted with bloud many a crimſon Croſſe. At length the Alarme was giuen, and the Ladders cleaude to the Wals, vp the aſſaylants climbde, vppe they lifted their fearefull weapons. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> not able (deſtitute of helpe) to withſtand them was taken priſoner, and his towre down raſed to the earth, with whoſe fall both the large Heauen and World ſhooke and quaked mightely, whom when they had fettered they left ther, they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out and the forenamed Chaires were preſently occupied with all the Imperiall rulers of Hell, who clothed in their holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day apparel ſat there to giue Iudgement vppon this wilfull <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> whom two Hangmans of Hell vnloofed, and there in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them all the great diuell afore his chiefe péeres, firſt ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with his angry foote, and then ſhaking his great buſhe of hair, that therewith he made the neare places and the moſt proud
<pb facs="tcp:178202:18"/> Diuels courages to tremble, and with his fire burnt ſcepter, and his like coloured Crown, all of gold, ſetting one arme by his ſide, and the other vppon the pummell of his Chaire, ſhooke a prettye ſpace with ſuch angry fury, that the flames which procéeded from his frightful eyes did dim the ſight of the Witte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers béelde. Ther was in this ſayd Wittenberg a gallant faire Lady and a virgin, which now following her mother accompanied with ſundry gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Germane Gentle-men, had euen nowe entred out of their Barge, and ſéeing the whole world of people as they thought ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp into the Heauen ſo very ſtrangely, were partly ſtroken with wonder, ſome with feare, and ſome with ſodaine merry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and haſting down the hill more then a round pace, asked ſome what was there to doe, and they bid them looke vp (for here is to be noted that they looked vp afore but could ſée nothing but as alwayes they were wont vntill they ſhewed them it) which they did, and at the ſame time wherein the great Diuell was in his red whot anger, this young Gentlewoman looked vp, whoſe moſt vgly ſhape ſo ſeared her, that euen then there ſhée fell downe in a ſown, whome they conuaied away very ſpéedily, yet ere they could come home ſhée was welnigh dead, and ſo ſhée lay for two yeares without hope of life, or certainty of death: great ſorrowe to her parents, and as cruell paine to her: But ſhée at length reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered hir Spirite, and if by your patience I may I will tell you how. There was a moſt learned and excellent Doctor dwelling in the Towne who had great knowledge in the blacke Art, who being requeſted to vſe ſome Phiſicke to aide her in her greate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, being promiſed for reward fiue thouſand Dollars. This Doctor perceiuing the cauſe of her malady was not cauſed of any diſtemperature of her body, but only of the afore ſayd feare, knew that Phiſicke might well make her body ſound, but her mind ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Wherefore not onely for the reward, but alſo to becom gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and famous at once, procéeded in his cure on this manner. One night hauing made his Oriſons and nine times combed his haire with teares of a pure maide, and nine times gone about a fire made all of pure Heben coale, and thrice nine times called vppon the name of the moſt dreadfull <hi>Hecate,</hi> he laide himſelfe to ſléepe vppon a pure white and cleane vnſpotted maidens ſmocke, and couered himſelfe ouer with the aſhes of a white Hind roſted
<pb facs="tcp:178202:18"/> and burned altogether, he ſlept, and the next morning apparelled in white robes, hauing often and often called, recalled, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed the thrée Fairies <hi>Millia, Achilya,</hi> and <hi>Sybilla</hi> at length the ground opened, and with them they brought a milke white Stéede, and did put vpon his finger the ring of inuinſibility, when they were vaniſhed, he mounted vp vppon his Horſe, who with more ſwift flight then the winged <hi>Pegaſus</hi> carried him throughe the wide Aire ſo faſt and ſo long, that hauing paſſed ouer <hi>Bohem, Hungary, Thracia,</hi> all <hi>Afin Minor, Meſopotamia,</hi> &amp; at length to <hi>Arabia, Foelix,</hi> where he alighted vppon a moſt high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, all the way from the top to the bottome of a iuſt bredth and ſtéepenes, ſo that he that were on that would thinke himſelfe not in the world, and they beneath would déeme him to be in heauen, vpon the brims of it round about grew the high Pines, the ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cedars, and alwaies ſo gréene as the moſt freſh Meddow: the height of this huge rocke was two and twenty miles in euen alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and halfe a mile of iuſt circuit all the way: there he tied his Horſe to a Trée and knocked at the Caſtle gate, where afore was neuer ſéene any, ſo that no path could there bée ſéene, ſo that a man might iuſtly haue called it the houſe of little Hoſpitality, to him there came <hi>Neglectment</hi> an old Lady, and demanded what he would, who told her his errand, and withall a ring of fine gold from the thrée Fairies, ſhée knew the ring and his errand, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayed him into many a fair roome, wherein ſhée ſhewed him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a worthy Knights memorials, many an antique Monument heaped vp, but inner roomes ſo monſtrous darke and nightly, that no humaine eie could perceiue any thing, and foorth ſhée brought him vnto a Garden, out of the midſt whereof roſe a little Hill fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſummity whereof, there was a paued way of pure Chriſtall ſtone, from along whoſe boſome trilled a ſmall Water: This wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an olde man helde, and in déede he had it as a Patrimony, for therefore he could ſhew many an auncient euidence, and worne Charter, his haire was all fled to his front, as if ſome enemy had ſcared the hinder locks from his ſcalpe, on his backe hung a paire of Wings which flagged downe, as if either they had béene bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or he weary, and thus he ouer ſtroad a round Worlde, from out if euery part whereof guſhed out this ſmall Riuer which was conuayed downe in this Chriſtall pipe, in his hand he held a long
<pb facs="tcp:178202:19"/> ſithe, and in the other an houre glaſſe, here the Doctor ſéeing the old ruines of this ſumptuous houſe, and all the faire Walles and buildings ouergroan with a deadly Moſſe was much amaſed, but becauſe he could not tarry, he dipt a ſmall Violl in the ſpring and departed, and for becauſe he was ſo peremptorily warned not to tarry, he could not behould the moſt ſtately Galleries, in which he might ſée the Worlds chiefe pleaſures and Monuments, ſome wholly worn away, ſome halfe, and ſome euen now beginning, and ſome wholy quite ouer-groane with a thicke earthye fur, for as he came by an old Wall he chaunſt with his elbow to rub off the thicke Moſſe, and then might hee ſée a faire péece of Parche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gilded and painted curiouſly, wherein was truely deſcribed the auncient tokens of a moſt braue and worthy Gentleman, ſo hauing ſped of his iourney he came by the ſame way againe as he went, <hi>Neglectment</hi> ſhut the doors vpon him, whilſt he mounted vppon his white ſwift footed Horſe and by the like time ariued at his owne houſe, where hauing with the bloud of a new ſlain hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, thrice annointed the féet of his <hi>Cauallo,</hi> and tying at his eare with a ſtring of fine ſilke ſpunne by the hands of a pure maid, the receiued ring of inuiſibility vnto his eare, with many a Croſſe, and many open <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> diſmiſſed him, who in the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment returned to the place from whence he came. With this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Doctor came to the maide, and hauing vſed a certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, gaue her to drinke of the water of déepe <hi>Obliuion,</hi> which ſhe had no ſoner taſted of, but ſtreight waies ſhe had forgot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten the terrible picture of the Diuell, and was reuiued out of all her infernall feares, the Doctor called winning him credite, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and fame, and richly rewarded for his medicine, departed, &amp; running whome threw his Violl into the déepe Riuer buryinge obliuion with obliuion, the parents of the young Lady reioyſing excéedingly at their daughters recouery, for euer after cauſed the place wherein their daughter was thus ſcared, to bee vnacceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for man or beaſt, compaſſing it in with a high wall, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the banckes, ſo that now there is no mention of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow nor of the Wall.</p>
               <p>The Diuell, the great Diuell <hi>Lucifer</hi> hauing finiſhed his briefe Oration, deſcended downe out of his Iudgement ſeat, and pointing vnto all his Nobles, tooke <hi>Fauſtus</hi> by the hand, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:178202:19"/> him iuſt before him, taking him by the chinne ſéemed to them to bid him ſpeake fréely, hee mounted vp againe vnto his high Throne, and with a more milde madneſſe expected the ſpéeche of the Doctor, who hauing bowed himſelfe ſubmiſſiuely vnto theſe damnable company, he began to ſpeake, and yet not long, then he began to walke vppe and downe and to ſhew ſtraunge geſtures, when ſodainely for ſome bugs words eſcaped by <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> all the Diuels there roſe vp, and with their ſwords drawen threatninge with them the poore Doctor, turning al their bodies and directing their faces to the King, who with a ſterne countenaunce com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded ſilence. When <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hauing long raged, of a ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine howling lowde, and tearing his haire, laide both his arms vppon his necke, and leapt down headlong of the ſtage, the whole company immediately vaniſhing, but the ſtage with a moſt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous thundering crack followed <hi>Fauſtus</hi> haſtely, the people ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thinking that they would haue fallen vppon them ran all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and he was happieſt that had the ſwifteſt foote, ſome leapte into the Riuer and ſwam away, and all of them with greate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright ranne into the Citty and clapt the Citty gates together, ſtreight, and to encreaſe this feare they thought they hard a thing fall into the riuer as if a thouſand houſes had fallen downe from the toppe of Heauen into it. But afterwards this was knowen to be <hi>VVagners</hi> knauery, who did this to ſhew the Purceuaunt ſome point of his skill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>THe meſſenger had not tarried aboue three dayes, when as <hi>Wagner</hi> had truſt vp his baggage, and was now readie to depart when on the third day at night he cauſe his boy <hi>Artur Harmaruan,</hi> (who was the ſonne of a wealthy boore, wittie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue manie, and praiſed for his notable waggery: his father dwelt at <hi>Malmesburg</hi> a town hard by <hi>Wittenberg</hi> in <hi>Saxony</hi> in high Dutchland, with whome <hi>Wagner</hi> being acquainted had obtained him of his father to ſerue him, and hee to be taught of <hi>Wagner</hi>) him he cauſe to go to diuerſe ſchollers of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to ſuppe with him at his departure, who being inuited to this hated farewell, came ſpéedily where they had a banquet and other curteſies which in ſuch a time both cuſtome and lawes of
<pb facs="tcp:178202:20"/> their fellowſhip doe preſcribe: In the ſupper time the ſchollers moued many queſtions, and amongeſt the reſt one deſired the purſeuant to deſcribe vnto them his Lord and maiſter, for they heard ſay that the Duke <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> was a maruellous quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Gentleman: The purſeuant not willing to refuſe their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt told them that ſeeing their demand procéeded of a common good zeale, he could not but wrongully refuſe to ſatiſfie: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the trueth might be better knowne of another then of him, when duetie bids to be partiall, if anie defect might breede partialitie, but ſo much as I will tell you, the enemie will not diſdaine to affirme: And there hee tolde them the very ſtature, proportion, and particular lineamentes, concluding that hee ſhewed the vprightneſſe of his minde by the proportion of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and keeping in his outward ſhape, the vertue which philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers would haue kept in the minde. There hee tolde them the feature of his countenance, the colour of his haire, eyes, face, chéekes, &amp;c. He tolde them his ſtature, fauour, and ſtrength, which was ſuch, that with pure cleanneſſe of his force, hee hath foyld a gentleman in wraſtling, who beſide wightneſſe of bodie, was very firme without affection, not as ſome doe which in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming any thing will with ſuch a ridiculous ſoureneſſe act it, as if the force of the bodie muſt be perſonated vppon the Theater of his face: He declared vnto them that the giftes of his minde were ſuch as then he could not for the number recken vp, but euen as occaſion ſhould ſerue might méete with them, being all ſuche as were more ready to be admired then imitated, as if all vertues were gathered in him together, magnanimity, magnificence, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fability, modeſty &amp;c. briefely (hée ſaide) there were in him all thoſe Graces, which adorne the ſubiect with the title of Vertuous. He likewiſe recounted vnto them his ſtudies, vnto which he accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated himſelfe at vacant houres, were partly the Poetry. A Poem of his he ſaide he had by chaunce gotten, (and by greater chaunce had it there at that inſtant) which hee had made in praiſe of his excellent Lady when he was but of young yeares, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liuing I dare ſay he would not for ten thouſand florens haue it ſéene, being ſuch a one as on a dreaming paſſion he had let fall from his penne and of many the moſt abiect, but ſuch as this is deſerues commendations, becauſe a Prince made it, but if you ſaw
<pb facs="tcp:178202:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> his reall deuiſes, you would then ſay they were Princelike. And then he read it, which I was loath my good friends either to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate or tranſlated to preſent it here, for that it was not worthie your cenſure, conſidering the nice buildings of <hi>Sonnets</hi> nowe a daies, but according to <hi>Ariſtos</hi> vaine you ſhall finde it very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmable, as alſo for that I knew that if I ſhould haue left it out, it would haue béene more wiſht for then now admirde. Yet for that I preferre your well knowen good wils afore any vain fear, take this with the reſt if they be any with ſuch fauor, as if I were by you at the reading.</p>
               <q xml:lang="ita">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A mio ſolemente amandona</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Madonna: Donna non parelia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>L' Angelico ſembiante e quel bel volte,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fa l'odio, e l'ira va in obliuione,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ch' a l' &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue I harſhly Engliſhed them verbally.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Angellike ſemblaunce beauties ornament,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Vertue quels all wrath and rancor deepe,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe life Heauens grace and death would monument</l>
                     <l>Vertue thy life are.<note place="margin">The Letter were worne out in this place.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>How many wounded hearts thou makſt to tremble,</l>
                     <l>And I of many one cannot diſſemble,</l>
                     <l>How farre into in <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> that ere-ſore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So were thy beauty but deſeruing praiſe,</l>
                     <l>So were thy beauty but as feminine,</l>
                     <l>Then could my quill his ſtraine ſo high arrayſe,</l>
                     <l>Then could with it compare the maſculine,</l>
                     <l>Thy beauty praiſe thy bounty ſpaſt diuine,</l>
                     <l>No ſtraine no quill ſuch wonderments aſſaies,</l>
                     <l>Then Poets pen ſhall to thy power his power reſigne,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What words may wel expreſſe ſuch excellence,</l>
                     <l>No humane thought thy beauties may compriſe</l>
                     <l>And wordes may tell al humane inſolence,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178202:21"/>
                     <l>All humane words and witte thy gifts ſurpriſe.</l>
                     <l>To ſatisfie my ſelfe in my pretence,</l>
                     <l>Our pen vnto the heauens muſt wander hence.</l>
                     <l>And fill it ſelfe with dew of heauenly Sapience.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And I my life ſhall to your hands reſigne,</l>
                     <l>VVhich liue to ſerue a humane Sainct ſo paſt deuine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <q xml:lang="ita">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Se da colei.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Che poco ingegno adhoradhor mi lima.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>This Sonnet was ended with as much praiſe as it beganne with deſire, and one of them coppied it out, and ſo it was made common to the reſt, &amp; made a good ſort of them Poets, rectifying their groſſe conceits, with ſo ſwéete a matter. He tould them that this was but a preparatiue to wondering in reſpect of his choiſe makings. Then he ſhewed them this Epigram, which he made when as before the Duke his Father, a brace of faire Engliſhe Grey hounds fell down at the Harts héels ſtarke dead, (the Hart alſo lying not aboue ſixe yards off dead to) with chaſing, hauing out ſtript the reſt of the dogs aboue halfe a mile.</p>
               <p>Then he reckonned vnto him the delight he tooke in <hi>Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,</hi> and ſhewed them very many fine deuiſes of his own han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy worke. The ſcollers ſingularly delighted with the viewe of the reliques of ſo great a Prince, approued by ſilence that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency which by ſpéech they could not. In fine there hee reckoned by enough to be prayſed, and peraduenture more then was true, but not more then is deſired. There he ſet forth with greate and ardent Emphaſis other qualities, as his skill and hardy demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at the Tilt turney, how he could menage the ſturdy ſteade, leape, run, vaunt, dance, ſing, play on diuerſe Inſtruments, and talke with amiable ſpéech amongeſt faire Ladies which wee call courting, in all his actions full of gentle familiar affability, ſtill reſeruing to himſelf the due honor belonging to his perſonage. He concluded in fine that he was the moſt qualified Prince and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Gentleman that day in all Chriſtendome: ſaying if they knew his humanity, iuſtice and liberality, you would ſay in him were all humanity, iuſtice and liberality: And as the greateſt thing that the world can ſhew is beauty, ſo the leaſt thinge that
<pb facs="tcp:178202:21"/> is to be praiſed, in him is beauty, you would ſay no leſſe then I haue ſpoken could be in his perſon if you did but ſée him. Thus far the digreſſion came in the commendations of this <hi>Alphonſus</hi> which truely I was weary of, fearing the great inſufficiency of the deſcription, but yet he had not done. I would to God (quoth he) you would come to Vienna and I promiſe you ſuch lodging &amp; entertainement, that next to the ſight of him ſhould be worthieſt of your thankes. Wherefore you ſhall not ſorrow that your frend <hi>Wagner</hi> departeth vnleſſe you will ſéeme to enuy rather his feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city then his departure. I would we were euen all of vs as wée ſitte at the Table in the Dukes Court, and here againe with a wiſh, and herewith their knockt one at the doore, <hi>Wagner</hi> crafte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayning that he himſelfe would riſe to ſée him that knockt ſo, deſiring them all to ſit ſtill in any caſe, and opening therwith the doore, there entred two young Lords of <hi>Tergeſte</hi> and <hi>Morauia,</hi> bearing Torches, &amp; next there came the Duke of <hi>Auſtrich,</hi> as they thought, &amp; <hi>Wagner</hi> talked with him bare headed (the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuant thinking verily it had béene his Maiſter, would haue done his duty vnto him, but that the reſt hindered him: on his heade he wore a little Hat of blew veluet, with a rich band of pearle, ſtone and gould, and a long white feather, his cloake of blewe veluet, round garded with gould lace, edged with Orient pearle, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the gards oylet holes whereout hung by ſmall ſilke thredes long bugles, all the ſléeues in the like order: by his ſide a golden hilted Rapier, and on his Rapier his hand, his Buskins of the fine Polonian leather, richly embrodered, on the turnings down with coſtly Gold-ſmiths worke, al his apparell whatſoeuer moſt beautiful and princely, he had no ſooner paſſed by (which was not vntill he was diſtinctly viewed of them) but that <hi>Wagner</hi> ſpake vnto them in ſuch manner: ſaying that that Honorable this mans Lord had ſent for him, whoſe commaundement I will in no wiſe repugne. Wherefore I beſéeche you to take it as you would my greateſt aduancement. This his deſcription of his feature, iudge how rightly he hath ſaide, for my part I confeſſe that they are rather leſſe then the trueth, then not as he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and herein to ſatisfie you the more I haue cauſed my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite <hi>Akercocke</hi> to take his ſhape vppon him.</p>
               <p>Now (quoth he) it is time to depart, but becauſe it ſhall bee
<pb facs="tcp:178202:22"/> the laſt night of our méeting none of you ſhall depart, for I haue lodging enough for you all, and for you ſhall not be forgetfull of <hi>Wagner</hi> when he is gone, let euery man wiſh his woman, and ſo to bed my maiſters. They began all to laugh merrely, not as hoping or wiſhing, but as if they had heard a merry purpoſe, and therefore they laughed becauſe it was merry, and ſuch mirth they alwaies liked off. <hi>VVagner</hi> was almoſt angry, and yet for that he was almoſt he was not angry, ſending out a great oath as the Prologue of his Comedy, bidding his Boy goe prepare theyr beds and chambers, and bid them wiſh whom they woulde, hée would their wiſhes ſhould be perfourmed. Then roſe vp one of the ſchollers perſwading himſelfe of <hi>VVagners</hi> earneſt, and yet doubting, becauſe he feared he was not in earneſt. Why (quoth he) if you meane in very déede my friend <hi>Kit.</hi> I would I had ſuch a woman, I beléeue beſide her ſelfe there is none fairer then the faireſt in this towne. Why wéeneſt thou I ieſt (quoth <hi>Wagner,</hi> goe thy waies, yonder ſhée is vppon paine of my head, and ſo it was in déede: then euery one ſtroue who ſhould wiſhe firſt, and he that wiſht laſt had his firſt wiſh, ſo euery one tooke his Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zel and for that night departed to their beds, who are witneſſes of that nights great pleaſures, &amp; in the morning they aroſe wiſhing that euery morning were the morrow of ſuch a night. Euery one gate him a Hackney, and brought him on the way a daies iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, where they with great griefe left him, who rode til he came to Vienna, and they till they arriued at Wittenberg. Thus ſtill you ſée theſe Potte méetings, are ended emongſt theſe puft-chéekt <hi>Hannikins</hi> with bed daliaunces, rightly deſcribing their liues moſt beſtiall and Epicure-like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>A lamentable hiſtory of the death of ſundry ſtudents of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg. CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>NOt long after it was reported and blaſed abroade that <hi>Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> was departed, diuerſe Schollers geſſing that he had left his Bookes or the moſt part behinde, determined to ſend for <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maruan,</hi> which they did, who by no perſwaſions could be wonne to let them haue his maiſters Keyes, ſo they deuiſed amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to bind the Boy as he ſhould goe home to his Inne, where
<pb facs="tcp:178202:22"/> as his Maiſter had put him to boord till his returne. And night drawing on <hi>Harmaruan</hi> went to his lodging, by the way ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to the number of ſeauen mette him and bound him, and beat him ſore vntill he gaue them all the Keyes, which he carefully ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about him ſowed in a wide Germane ſloppe, which when they had (they being all muffled and diſguiſed ſtrangely with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards) they looſed, and then they ran haſtely to <hi>VVagners</hi> houſe, as if they had fled from followers, or elſe followed ſome haſtelye flying, wher being come, they opened the gates, and being entred ſhut them again, this being about eleuen of the clocke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night, &amp; in they went, where they found two Barrels of mighty ſtrong March Engliſh Béere of two years old, which they broched, and ſate ſo long drinking till they were all well druncke. And then downe they get into a backe Court, and hauing lighted Tapers, hauing iniuriouſly framed all the circles, ſquares, triangles, &amp;c. and apparelled with all the coniuring roabes that the Art requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, there they begin in a moſt dreadfull confuſion of helliſhe ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables to enforme the Féend, and after theſe words followed as if there néedes muſt ſuch thinges follow after ſuch words, a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble roare, and then ſo bright a ſmoothring thick fiery fume aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of the earth as if it woulde haue made an eternall night, then a vehement flame followed which with continuall motion, ran about the brims of the circle, vntill as weary it left moouing, (all this while they continued reaſonably conſtant, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their inuocations without any feare) then from beneath was heard moſt lamentable outcries, from aboue huge trembling, thunder, and round about nothing but feare and death in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand terrible diuerſe ſhapes, then they began to quaile a little, but yet by encouragement grew hardy by reaſon of the number, then round about was ſounded alarms with drums, and oneſette with Trumpets, as if there all the World had conflicted, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flame which all this while ran about the circle became a body, but ſuche a body, as if it had béene but a Picture woulde haue madded any one. At whoſe ſight they wholy ouercome with deadly fear for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat the vſe of their Pantacles or any ſuch geare, but euen ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues to the ſmall mercy of the Féend, who with great violence rent them and fore them moſt lamentably. <hi>Harmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uan</hi> who had raiſed a great many to the intent to follow them ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting
<pb facs="tcp:178202:23"/> that which in déede was, was after long wandring (for they had cauſed a Diuell diſcrier to voide all within a certain cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite) with his company brought to the houſe, where rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout they might ſée in the Court wherein theſe ſeauen were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuring, huge flames as if ſome great pile had béene made to the buriall of a noble <hi>Heroie,</hi> climing vp in huge volumes vppe into the Aire, or if ſome great ſtore of ſtuble had béene fired, ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently furious was the flame that no man there (and there were aboue thirty) was able once to draw neare to any part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe, the cry was carried into the Citty of this fire, whereuppon the whole towne was aſſembled with hookes, buckets, ladders, &amp;c. where in vaine they emptied many a large Well, till diuers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Preachers falling downe ſubmiſſiuely on their knées, with good faith appeaſed this ſéeming fire which in déede was none, but a méere diabolicall illuſion, then they entred into the houſe, wher they found the Barrels brought a bed and deliuered, the cups, the whole furniture cleane deſtroyed, broken, and throne about the Houſe, but drawing neare vnto the moſt ruefull and lamentable ſpectacle of all, comming into the yeard or groue which was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about and encloſed with a thicke Wall of trées very excéeding high, as Firre trées are, ſo very thicke that no light was pearce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able into it, in the very midſt whereof was a round plot of ſome one hundred foote any way from the Centre, there found they the religious Circles, there the ſtrange Characters, names of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, a thouſand Croſſes, there founde they the fiue croſſe hilted Daggers for the fiue Kings of Hell, there many a ſtrong bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke builded with rowes of Croſſes, there found they the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſes, the ſtoles, pall, miters, holy water, pots broken, their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riapts, ſeats, ſignes of the Angels of the ſeauen daies, with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite like traſh and damnable roggery, the fruites of the Diuels rancke fanſie. But the moſt lamentable ſight of all the ſeauen Schollers vtterly torne in péeces, their bloud hauing chaunged the colour of the ground into a darke Crimſon, al their bodies as blacke as any coale as if they had béene ſcorcht with a materiall fire, their fleſh violently rent from the bones, and hanging down in morſels like the skirts of a ſide coate, their bones all broaken, their vaines cut in ſunder, and their bowels broad ſhed vppon the earth, their brains powred out and couering the red graſſe all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:23"/> their notes ſtimtyed, their eies thruſt out, their mouths wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſlit vp to the eares, their téeth daſht out, and their tongue ſtarting out betwixt their gums, their haire cleane ſinged of, in briefe imagine with your ſelues in your minds, and propounde a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cture in your thought, the moſt deformed, borne, and ill fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that you can thinke on, yet ſhall it not compare to the moſte lachrimable ſight and ſhew of them, ſurpaſſing as much all cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite as my skill dewly to deſcribe them, whom when they had buried without tarriaunce, raced the houſe to the ground, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vppe the moates with earth, heaping vppon the place of this murther the ſtones of the houſe defaced, then they returned home diſcourſing with lamentable iudgement vppon the high and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere reuenge of Gods indignation vppon them which durſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to tempt his glorious Maieſty. And finally vnleſſe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce bréede a more ſpéedy remorſe ſuch is the fatall end of ſuche proude attempts. And ſurely this is moſt true, for I my ſelfe haue ſéene the ground wher the houſe ſtood, and yet the moates damde vp and the Water breaking throw ths ſtones euen to this day, there did I ſée a skull and a ſhancke bone of them not yet rotten: and there did I ſée the huge heape of ſtones wherewith they are couered, a fearefull example of Gods wrath and iuſtice agaynſt ſuch infidell Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>THe great Turke called <hi>Souldan, Alias Cham,</hi> comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as many victories in his ſworde as ſome Emperours in their thoughts arriued at length afore Vienna, hauing made his preamble with the deſtroying and burning of the countrey before him, thinking vpon the ancient pollitick rule, <hi>Better it is to haue a ſpoyled countrey then a loſt,</hi> with a braue prepared Army of two hundred thouſand Saracens, horſe and foote, and ſo many it is certain he had, becauſe they doubted not but ther were 300000 The mighty <hi>Cham</hi> hauing erected his royall Pauilions, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched himſelfe to beſiege the noble Vienna, munified his camp with Artillery and déepe ditches, and then he ſent a Letter of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce vnto the Honorable <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> as being principall in his owne Citty, who was enuironed within the wals of the citty expecting the day of battell, for to this entent the ſtates of Italye
<pb facs="tcp:178202:24"/> and the Emperour of Germany, with the Dukes of Saxony, Bauaria, and the other Prouinces neare aſſembled (for now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity bred vnity) with a braue company of Souldiers to exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate this monſter out of their confines: vnto the Duke of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrich onely (for he had no intelligence of their aſſembled forces) he directed his Letters with defiance, meaning to conclude his long trauailes with a certaine victory: fearing neither the peril which ſo many gallant ſouldiers throughly reſolued might bring, nor that euer God or fortune (as they call it) would once ſhew him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny disfauour, whoſe onely fauour is onely in ſhew. Nor yet that the heauens great God would not with ſeuere reuengement cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe the <hi>Leuiathans</hi> inſolency and ſlaughter of ſo many Martirs, rather deferring then forgetting ſo iuſt a puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>ABout this time the Meſſenger and <hi>Wagner</hi> arriued at Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na very late in the night and paſſed through the Turkiſhe Sentinels, and arriuing at the Citty, and for that night they lay at the Purceuants houſe, no ſooner had the approaching Sunne ſent afore him the marſhals of the morrow light, and a new mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning miniſtred occaſion of new matter, but vp thoſe two aroſe &amp; being ready departed for the Courte, and now the day was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the greateſt beauty, when the Meſſenger was admitted into the Dukes preſence, vnto whom he recited what euer was ſéene, and done in that time of his abſence, (only I forgot to tell you how <hi>Wagner</hi> raged and ſtormed, and thundered, when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercocke</hi> brought him word of the deſtruction of his Houſe at Wittenberg as he was in the way to Auſtria) wherewith the Duke was wonderfully both delighted and aſtoniſhed. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wellcommed <hi>Wagner</hi> very graciouſly and accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, he diſmiſſed them till further leaſure, commaunding the Purceuant to ſhew him all the pleaſure he mought.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>AFter al theſe moſt excellent Princes were come into the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell chamber, the Herrald ſounded his trumpet after the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſhe ſummons then did all the ſtates draw into the great Hall, wherin a high Imperiall throne richly ordered with ſhining cloth
<pb facs="tcp:178202:24"/> of Gold, euery noble and eſtate placed correſpondently to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée, where in preſence of them all the Herralde was admitted, who comming with his coate of Armes lying vppon his right arme into the bottome of the Hall, made thrée obeyſances downe with the right knée vnto the ground, with a loud &amp; diſtinct voice ſpake vnto the Duke onely, telling him that his ſoueraigne and Maiſter <hi>Soultan Alias Chan,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Murad Chan,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Rabeck Chan,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Mahomet Chan,</hi> and ſo vpwards till he came to their great Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> God on the earth, and Emperour of all the Eaſt. And then he began to reckon fiue hundred titles, with a long &amp;c.. Vnto thée <hi>Alphonſus</hi> Arche-Duke of Auſtrich, and there he declared the whole effectes of his meſſage, and at laſt with a great Brauado ended, and then he did one his gaie coate of Armes expecting their aunſwere. When as the Duke crauing licence of the Emperour to ſpeake anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Herrauld in moſt gallant and triumphing tearms, commanding him to ſay vnto the proud Turke his maiſter, that ere fiue dayes came about he would trample his victorious horns vnder his féet, and ride in triumph vppon his ſtubborne necke, and that in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of himſelfe and of braue Chriſtendome hee woulde léeſe the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt drop of his bloud, &amp; to make it good hee would not be in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et till he had met his maiſter in the midſt of the field, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he drew out his ſword, and all they with him, crying God &amp; Sainct <hi>Michaell</hi> for the right of Chriſtendome: then ſtoode vppe the Emperour and auowed all that they had ſaide afore him, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding moreouer the Herrald to ſay to the proude Vſurper, that ſéeing the quarrell would bréede great effuſion of bloud, and yet he neuer the nearer, that he a man euery way equall to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, not onely for the ſpéedier aduaunce of his battels, but alſo to haue a certaine end to ſuch an vncertaine enterpriſe, hee woulde fight with him body to body, armed at all points after their owne guiſe at any time within this fortnight, and Herrald bring mee word (quoth he) that he will ſo doe, and by my Honor I promiſe to giue thée for thy tidings 10000. Duckets. Then the Herralde being highly rewarded was diſmiſſed, and reported their braue aunſweres vnto the Turke, with all the great maieſty of the Chriſtian Princes, who preſently went to counſell together, and ſo continued till other like neceſſary buſines called them away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:178202:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <p>IN this Chapter (Gentlemen) parte of the Dutch coppy was wanting, and the other part ſo rent that it could not be red, yet by ſome circumſtances I coniecture that the Duke of Auſtriche had diuerſe and dangerous conflicts with the Turke, yet beeing ſupported by the Engliſhe men and other Chriſtians, with the help of <hi>Wagner,</hi> who ſtanding in a high towre to ſee the conflicts, cauſed by his Magicke ſuch a ſtorme to ariſe that no man was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to abide, the Turke was ſtil diſcomfited.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>The giftes of Wagner to the Duke, and three Diuels retaind for Souldiers to the ſame Prince. CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>IN the next morning <hi>VVagner</hi> preſented himſelfe to the Duke in preſence of all the whole Princes of the Chriſtians, whom very graciouſly he entertained as he might for his good ſeruice, &amp; there in preſence of them al he deſired the Duke to take at his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants hands a ſmall gift, which hee condiſcended vnto, and then <hi>VVagner</hi> cauſed a Cheſt to be brought in of fine Iron, wrought and inameld with gould and colour moſt curiouſly, then hee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it and tooke out a whole armour of fine bright ſtéele ſo light as a common Dublet, but ſo ſubtelly and excellently framed, that it paſſed all compariſon of hardneſſe, there was a Musket ſhotte at euery péece whereon remained no great notice of a blow, but as of a little touch, plaine without any broider worke or otherwiſe carued, but ſo excéeding bright as would well haue dazeled the long beholders eies, a ſhield of the ſame faſhion, made like a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toyle ſhell, a ſword of the like fine temper, with all the furniture of a ſouldier, then tooke he out a Plume which hee had no ſooner put into the creſt, but he that ſtoode behinde coulde not ſée no part of his backe, nor he that ſtoode before of his breſt, ſo that thus it made him inuiſible, ther he told him it was fetcht out of the great Turks armory, which they ſay was <hi>Mahomets,</hi> but I ſay more truely <hi>Alias Chans,</hi> which for himſelfe cauſed it to be made, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing called together the moſt excellent Philoſophers and worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were to be found in all his wide Empire. The great rewards the Duke would haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him for it he refuſed, he was only contented with thankes and fauor. And then might they ſee
<pb facs="tcp:178202:25"/> from the doore of the chamber thrée moſt gallaunt men to enter, which were his thrée Familiars, whom <hi>VVagner</hi> taking by the hands preſented vnto the whole aſſembly of Princes, but more directly to the Duke, aſſuring them that they were the moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, moſt valiant, ſtrong, hardy, and puiſſant men that in the World were to be found, and in déede they ſéemed to be as goodly ſwart men as any eie beheld, he tould their ſeuerall names <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſtophiles</hi> he tearmed <hi>Mamri, Akercocke</hi> he tearmed <hi>Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onte, Fauſtus</hi> hee called <hi>Don infeligo,</hi> ſhewing that they were borne in thoſe fortunate Ilands, wherein the Poets fained the Elyſian fields to be, ioyning by Weſt vpon the end of Barbary, being from Vienna to thoſe fortunate Ilands 35. degrées of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude and eight minutes, and 48. degrées and 22. minutes from the <hi>Aequator</hi> or <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> in latitude not then founde out. So were they moſt graciouſly entertained of all the Nobles, and entertained in the Dukes moſt Honorable pay. <hi>VVagner</hi> ſaid that they thrée left their countrey and ſought aduentures, and by chaunce comming this way, I knowing of it by ſecrete intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, met them and certainely aſſured of their high valours, thought good to ſhew them to you, for hee that firſt had ſpoake to them had béene firſt ſerued, nor cared they whether to ſerue vs or the Infidell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Spake before of a challenge made by the Emperour vnto the Turke, which when the Herrald had reported vnto the <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> (who certainely was a verye honorable Souldier) but there he vowed to performe it, and to ſet the Emperours head vppon his higheſt pauilion in view of all the Citty. And thereuppon the next day after this skirmiſhe, he ſent the ſame Herrald with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and commandement to declare in excellent gallant tearmes the acceptance of the combate, knowing that it depended vppon his honor to ſhew his ſmall feare, in not refuſing ſo equall a Foe, whoſe profer procéeded from a moſt Honorable reſolution: when it was reported vnto the Empepour that the ſame Herralde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, he cauſed the Hall to bee adorned with moſt braue furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, his high Chaire of eſtate placed, and all about ſeates for the other Princes. The Emperour hauing ſeated himſelfe, full of
<pb facs="tcp:178202:26"/> braue thought and gallant hardyhood, expecting the aunſwere of the enemy in ſuch ſort as it was in very déede. In all braue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Herrald in proud phraſe vttered the purport of his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, requeſting that a peace being concluded on both partes for the ſpace of thrée daies, and frée egreſſe and regreſſe for the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles on both parties the one to viewe the Campe, the other the Court, and on the third day he would armed in his countrey ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner méete him in the liſtes, to ſhew that he neuer refuſed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of any Chriſtian Emperour, albeit he knew his calling far ſuperior to that of his. So then the meſſage was accepted, the Herrald had his 10000. Duckets carried to the Turkes campe on horſe, and they in the Citty began to kéepe feaſts, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Turkiſh Nobles in excéeding brauery, and they theirs in the like without damage or thought of treaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>DVring the time of this truce, theſe foure companions, <hi>Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligo, Wagner, Mamri, Symionte,</hi> caſt how to abuſe the great Turke moſt notably, and <hi>Akercocke</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Symion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> he would begin firſt, and lead them the dance. Then he leaues them and gets me vp vnſéene to the Turkes Campe, and in his Campe to his own Pauilion, &amp; ſo into the place where the great Infidell himſelfe ſate, he being then gone into the Lauatory, which is a place wherein he thrée times a day doth bathe himſelf, which by ſo doing he doth verily beléeue that all his ſinnes are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and waſhed away be they neuer ſo horrible, diueliſhe, or wicked, then <hi>Akercocke</hi> or <hi>Symionte,</hi> which yée wil, goes inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly into the Lauatory, where the great Villaine was bathing himſelfe amongeſt thrée of his moſt faire Concubines ſtarke na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſwimming as much in their dalliance as in the water, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling his waſhing with kiſſes and his cleanſing with voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <hi>Akercock</hi> in the ſhape of a bright Angell appeares vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and with a proud <hi>magnifico</hi> preſented himſelfe vnto the ſlaue, who ſtraight waies very reuerently fell downe vppon his knées, and with his hands high lifted vp, worſhipped towardes him in great humility, whilſt <hi>Akercocke</hi> with good deuotion fell a boord the Concubines, and there acted them before his face one after another: when he had ſo done, he takes the greate ſlaue by
<pb facs="tcp:178202:26"/> the tip of his pickenouant, agd ſhaking him fiercely (who al this while with great dreade and feare lay halfe aſtoniſhed and al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on the ground) told him that hee had prepared a more brauer place for his ſo good a ſeruaunt then ſo baſe a bathe, and no fairer Concubines. (Now the Turke had ſéene how like a luſty rancke fellow this <hi>Simionte</hi> had behaued himſelfe, at which he wonders not greatly, becauſe <hi>Fauſtus</hi> whom he thought to haue béen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> (as well as he did thinke <hi>Akercocke</hi>) had alſo ſhewed the vertue of ſo great a God as <hi>Mahound,</hi> twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty times more beauty then <hi>Iupiter.</hi>) Then the Turkiſh Emperour with halfe dyinge hollow voice, as if his breath had béene almoſt gone or elſe but now comming, ſaid that he was all at his commandement, and ſo followed <hi>Simionte</hi> ſtarke naked as he was born, who led him by the hand rounde about, and through euery Lane and place of his Campe, to the great wonderment &amp; laughter of his people, who verily thought <hi>Mahound</hi> had commanded him to do penance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he fought with the Chriſtian Emperour. But for al this the people fell into ſuch laughter that ſome had welnigh giuen vp the Ghoſt at the ſame inſtant, diuers Chriſtian Nobles ſaw him all this while, who effuſedly laughed at ſo apparaunt foolery. The Turke for all this not moued, for indéede hee heard all and ſawe nothing, went about wonderfully mannerly: like as you ſhall ſée a Dutch Frow with a handkercheife in her hand mince it after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hopping Germane. Could a man deuiſe a more notorious kinde of abuſe, then to make that man which will not bee ſéene but in great ſecrecy, and aboundantly and richly clad, to bee not onely ſéene openly but alſo ſtarke naked, &amp; becom their laughing ſtocks whoſe terrour he is alwaies, but <hi>Akercocke</hi> had not yet ſo lefte him, but downe he runs to <hi>Danuby</hi> (where there was readye <hi>Mamri</hi> or <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> to receiue him) and there hauinge turned himſelfe &amp; the vileſt part of himſelfe to the Turks mouth, making him kiſſe and kiſſe it againe, he tooke him and hurld him violently into the Water, and then <hi>Akercocke</hi> vaniſhed away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond mocking. CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <p>NO ſooner was he in but he ſaw then apparantly how hée had béene miſ-led and abuſed, and there for very ſhame woulde
<pb facs="tcp:178202:27"/> haue drownd himſelfe in very déede, had not <hi>Mamri</hi> come ſwiftly flying ouer &amp; gaue him a terrible blowe on the noddle with a good Baſtinado, that he almoſt made his braines flye out, and rapte him vp by his long haire out of the water vnto the land, wher he buffeted him ſo long till at length he came to himſelfe againe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Mamri</hi> fewtred himſelf to abuſe him kindly, and there with ſwéet and compaſſionatiue ſpéech comforted him, deſiring his reuerend Maieſty not to take any griefe ſéeing it was doone in the ſight of all his men, in the knowledge of none. And therewith to ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more pitty of his miſery he ſéemed to ſhed aboundance of teares, deſiring him to goe with him and he would put vpon him his ſoft raiment. The Turke (who then had his crowne vpon his head or elſe it had not béene halfe in the right <hi>Qu</hi>) ſéeing one lamenting his caſe ſo affectionatly, condiſcended vnto him and promiſed him moſt large honorable promotion and reward. <hi>Mamri</hi> ſet him v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his legs and led him to a little muddy place by the riuer ſide, and there varniſhed the Emperour ouer with moſt thicke, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and excrementall mud, not ſparing either his face, noſe, eies, mouth, nor any thing, whilſt he miſerable man thought hee had béene in moſt diuine contentment. Thus he led him in the viewe of fiue thouſand people (for here is to bee noted that all that euer ſaw him both knew him to be the great villain Turke, and could not but laugh moſt entirely at him, nor his owne men could do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other nor once thinke of any reſcue or remedy, by the working of infernall inſtinct) vntill he came to Vienna, and in Vienna to the moſt faire gates and where greateſt reſort of people are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies together, there at the Citty gate he drew out a long taber and a pipe and ſtrikt vp ſuch a merry note, as the fooliſh orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of all London ſtages neuer could come neere him, no not when he wakte the writer of the newes out of Purgatory, with the ſhrill noiſe. Ther at the gate ſtood a Carpenter who was then carrying a Coffin to a certain houſe to bury one in, him <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> beate till hee laie on the could ground, and tooke the Coffin and cauſed the Turk to hold it in his hand. <hi>Memorandum</hi> that none of all theſe Spirites were ſéene of any one, but felt of them which ſaw them. Then from the gate he began to play, the Turke and the Coffin skipt and turnd, and vaunted, and bounded, and leapt, and heaued, and ſprung ſo faſt and ſo thicke together, that the cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin
<pb facs="tcp:178202:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> rapping the miſſerable man ſometime on the ſhinnes, breaſt, thighes, head, face, that the durty colour was almoſt wipte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the ſtreames of bloud. At this ſtraunge fight and the vnheard noiſe of that kinde of Inſtrument, al the boies, girls, and roags in the town were gathered with this troupe, &amp; this mirth, he conuaied them round about the ſtréets, and al the way as they went, ſuch egs, ſuch chamber pots emptyings, ſuch excrements, odoure, water, &amp;c. were throwne down on their heads, that it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all thoſe vile matters were reſerued for that Tempeſt, vntill ſuch time (then it being about two of the clocke in the afternoone when euery one is buſied in ſome pleſaunt paſtaunce) as all this faire company came to the Court, whereout at diuerſe windows lay the chiefeſt of all the Nobility, and the moſt braue Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who ſéeing ſuch a huge crowd of Boyes, the great Turke and a Coffin dauncing, and a taber and pipe playd vppon, they were almoſt amaſed, thus hee marched finely round aboute the whole Court, till comming to the Court gate he entred in, (but the Boyes were excluded) with this merry Morris there in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them all the Turke fell downe dead, whom <hi>Mamri</hi> layd in the Coffin, and then vaniſhed away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>The thirde. CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <p>THen came <hi>Infeligo</hi> or <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and touching him reuiued him to the great wonder of the beholders, and couering him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſhamefaſtly, went into his chamber with him, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notted him round vpon the head and the beard, which is the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt reproch and diſgrace that can be offered to the Turke, which done he conuaied him into the preſence of the Emperour, where hee made them ſuch ſporte, that vnneath they could recover their modeſty in thrée houres ſpace, to ſée the proud Villaine plaiſtered ouer with ſuch muddy morter, all euer his head and face, his eyes and téeth ſhewing like black Moores, or as a paire of eies looking through a Lettice, or as they cal it a Periwig, wherein if the eies had féete they might be ſet in ſhe ſtocks: All his lineaments were lineamented with this pariet, he ſtood quiuering and ſhaking ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for could or feare like an Aſpine leafe (as they ſay) whileſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man buffeted him, he ſtanding with a ſturg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtice and an old
<pb facs="tcp:178202:28"/> ſhooe, as they doe at blind man buffe to ſée who he could hit. Thus long he made them ſport, till one tolde the Emperour that it was the great Turke, at which he was excéeding wroth and ſorry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth and laſt. CHAP. XX.</head>
               <p>VVHen <hi>Wagner</hi> ſéeing him grieued, came and knéeled downe before him, declaring that he would vndertake to heale all his wounds and other gréeueances whatſoeuer, yea &amp; make him vtterly forget al that was paſſed as if it had neuer béene, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed more to carry him home himſelfe ſafe and ſound, which the Emperour thanked him highly for, requeſting him to performe it preſently, for hee would not for halfe his reuenews that his Foe ſhould haue any occaſion to alledge againſt him, for to excuſe the Combate. Then went <hi>Wagner</hi> vp into his chamber, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled himſelfe in white tafita made cloſe to his bodye, and there where they vſe to weare round hoſe halfe a foote déepe, ſtuck with ſwans feathers, like the skirts of a horſmans coat, his hoſe, ſhoos, (for all were together) of the ſame white tafita, and within with white leather, at his héeles two fine ſiluer wings, &amp; on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders two maruailous large bright ſiluery wings, and on his head an vpright little ſtéeple hat (with a white feather of two or thrée ranges) of white tafita, and in his hand a <hi>Caduceus</hi> or a <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi> Rod in the ſame white ſiluer colour, hee entred into the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence Chamber afore all the aſſembly to their ſingular contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for in his Perſonated garments he ſéemed to be a very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, for it was in doubt whither <hi>Mercury</hi> was halfe ſo beautiful or no. And there opening a large caſement (as there they are very large) with a braue <hi>R'ingratio</hi> departed from them taking vp his flight in the view of them all into the aire, as if hee woulde haue beate the Azure firmament with his waſt wings. Thus he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him lower and lower till he did light vpon a great Elme, and there he opened his ſight to ſée in what plight he was. The Turk ſéeing in what a traunce he had béene, began to ſweare, to banne and curſe, and was euen then ready to haue thrown himſelf down headlong, but <hi>Mercury</hi> hee ſtept to him and bad him bee of good chéere, for it had pleaſed the great God <hi>Iupiter,</hi> whoſe ſeruaunt <hi>Mahomet</hi> was, to ſhew him thoſe great abuſes, to the intent he
<pb facs="tcp:178202:28"/> ſhould be more wary in his actions, and take héede how to tempt the Chriſtians with vaine battels and ſuch like ſpéech, but nowe (quoth he) come and giue me thy hand, and thern will I lead thée to thy Pauilion, where as yet thou art not miſſed of the Nobles, for in the place where thou waſt taken away, hath <hi>Ioue</hi> ſent one to beare thy ſhape. Then againe he tooke his flight &amp; all the way as he went he rapt his héels againſt the tops of the high trées, and beat him pittifully vppon the ſhins al the iourney, vpon the tents tops. Now they arriued in the ſame place from whence hee was tane. and there he laide himſelfe domn who preſently recouered his former ſtrength in ful perfectneſſe, and not onely not felt it but vtterly forgat it. Then he continued his wonted ſolace and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared himſelfe to the battaile, whileſt hee was made a laughinge ſtocke of the world, <hi>Wagner</hi> returned through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame path which he had made in the aire before, came not yet to the Court before they had done laughing, for there the matter from the beginning to the end was rehearſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>The proceſſe to the combate. CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <p>THe two daies of the truce were paſſed and the third morning was come, in which time many gallaunt feates of armes and actiuity were performed on both parts. Now the time of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate was come. There was in the Riuer of Danuby a pretty I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of a quarter of a mile long or more, as euen as ground might be all the way, in this place were the liſts prepared, and a ſcaffold richly hanged for the Iudges to determine in. In the euening a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout foure of the clocke (being then reaſonable coole) The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour iſſued out with aboue 100000. Chriſtians, the reſt being aboue 60000. were left to defend the Citty (for both the Chriſtian and eſpecially the Turkes were increaſed) wher he entred into the wide plaine, and comming to the bancks ſide hee entred into a broad Ferry boate leauing his whole Armye on the other ſide of the Riuer whileſt he laboured to attain to the Iland. The Duke of Auſtria with his attendants <hi>Mamri, Simionte, Infeligo,</hi> and <hi>Wagner,</hi> the Dukes of Clebe, Saxony, Campany, and Brabant, with the like number all brauelye and gloriouſly mounted: The Duke of Auſtria in his bright armour marſhalled
<pb facs="tcp:178202:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> the field, and of the Chriſtian ſate as Iudges the kings of Luſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany and Arragon with their Herralds: Now the Emperour is landed in the Iſland and is mounted into his rich ſaddle, armed in armour ſo coſtly, ſtrong, curious, and reſplendeſcent, that it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med al the beauty in the world had béene gathered together in it, his courſer ſo firme, nimbly ioynted, tall and large, ſuch a one might haue béene the ſon of <hi>Gargantuas</hi> more for his Giant-like proportion. Then tooke he his ſtrong and large Aſken lance, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his ſtéele head Iron death, at the top whereof hung a fair and rich pennion, the whole ſhaft of the ſpeare double g lded ouer and curiouſly enameld, about his necke hung his horne ſhield, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially adorned with his owne atchieuement, the belt whereon his ſword hung of beaten gold, his capariſon of pure cloth of gold, whereon the rich ſtones were ſo ordinary that they tooke away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glittering of the mettall onely as if it had béene the Sun beames, trailed along betwixt precious gutters. On his helmet was fixed a rich Crown of the moſt excellent mettall. In briefe for I would faine haue made an end of this idle newes, there was all the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in his Empire in that all the beauty of his richnes, in them al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire of each eie: when he had ſaluted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudges he trotted twice or thriſe about the liſts, and then lighted at his Pauilion which was there erected of cloth of gold, where he ſate with conuenient company and refreſhed himſelfe. Now in the meane the Turke he ſet forward with an army double the chriſtian, and 100000. and aboue ſtill left in the Campe. And here I muſt néedes leaue to tell you of his excéeding preparation vnleſſe I ſhoulde make a whole volume, for beſide the wondrous furniture of his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the moſt rare choiſe of ornaments, there was nothing could be deuiſed, nay more then of ſet purpoſe could be deuiſed was ther. But briefely I will turne to the Turke himſelfe, where if I had art according, I ſhould ſooner weary you with delight the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> words: But 100000. of his men hauing marched before to the banckes and there embatteled themſelues by the riuer all along, with ſuch hideous noiſe of Trumpets horns (for ſo they vſe) drums of bras, fluites &amp;c. that there was more heard then ſéene by farre, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached the great Turke himſelfe, before him rode 4000. <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſaries</hi> armed in their faſhion, with a long Gowne of Scarlet red laced with gold lace, &amp; long ſléeues of a verye narrow bredth,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:29"/> which was girt cloſe vnto him, vnder that a good armour, with a long high cap like a milke pale for all the world, of white Satten or ſome ſuch like gear, with a long feather enough to come down to a tall mans hams, very thick laced in the brims with gold and pearle, in his hand a ſhort Iauelin, at his ſide his Cemiter, at his backe a great Quiuer of broad arrowes, and by a ſtring of ſilke hung his ſtéele bow, ouer euery 100. of theſe is a <hi>Boluch Baſſa</hi> a Centurien as we call him, and theſe be of the Turks guard, and are called <hi>Solaquis Archers,</hi> and they rode fifty in a rancke, then came following the about 200. <hi>Peicher</hi> or <hi>Peiclers,</hi> all in one liuery of very rich tiſſue after their faſhion, and theſe are of the Turkes <hi>Laqueis</hi> which haue a ſharpe téene Hatchet ſticking at their girdels, and the haſt of Braſill, with this they will ſtande 30. paces off and cleaue a penny loafe or hit it ſome where, they will commonly ſticke an inche and halfe déep into a very tuffe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen wood, or a Braſill, or ſuch like hard wood: there in great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph vppon an Elephant richly trapped, ſtood a Towre of two yardes and a halfe high of pure ſiluer, in the top whereof ſtood an Image of beaten gold, repreſenting their <hi>Mahomet,</hi> rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which vpon Mules <hi>Azamoglans</hi> or <hi>Iamoglans,</hi> who are children of tribute exacted vpon the Chriſtian captiues, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributary, fine, ſwéete, and the moſt choiſe picked Gentlemen brought vp to ſundry dainty qualities, who with heauenly melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy followed this Elephant, the religious men going round about ſinging ſwéetely together: afore all theſe next to the <hi>Ianiſſaries</hi> went aboue 200. Trumpets, and as many followed the greate Turke, who then approached, hauing his Chariot of pure ſiluer of aboue 20000. pound weight, drawne with eight milke white Elephants, round about rode and went bare headed, <hi>Azamog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans Peyclers</hi> moſt gorgeouſly and reſplendeſcent appareled, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Turkes féete lay a pillow of cleare Chriſtall emboſſed at the ends with huge golden knobs, on his head a wreath of purple with a moſt rich diadem as it is comely knowen the order of it, the ſtage can ſhew the making of it, but other thinges they differ mightely in. Here you muſt ſuppoſe the excéeding glory of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, there he ſate vpright in the Chaire with ſuch a maieſtical, proud, ſeuere, warlike countenaunce, as iuſtly became ſo high a throne, before him went <hi>Aga</hi> which is the great Captaine of his
<pb facs="tcp:178202:30"/> 
                  <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> with the <hi>Hali Baſſa,</hi> the Captaine of his nauall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions, <hi>Bianco Baſſa</hi> the Captaine of his <hi>Ianiſſarie</hi> Harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhiers, the <hi>Zanfyretto Baſſa</hi> captaine of his guard, with other of great authority bare headed. After his Chariot came ſwéete melody, and then fiue Elephants of War (an Elephant is wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh as big as ſixe Oxen gant and ſlender like a horſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> franks, and of more ſwift foote then a man would thinke for, his faſhion is like no beaſt in England, but the ridge of his backe is like that of an borſe, his féete hath fiue great horny toes, and a very longe ſnoute of aboue two yards in length, with which he will draw by onely ſnuffing vp a good pretty big lad, and deliuer him to the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this long trunck fals downe betwixt a large paire of teeth or tuſhes of aboue an Ell and a halfe long (as yee may commonlye ſée at the Combe makers in London) bending like a Bores vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, his eares welnigh from the top to the neither tippe of the hanging downe aboue ſeuen foote long.) And after theſe fiue E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants, ſadled and ordered for a man to ride on, came tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pets, and all in the like manner as before, and then marched 500. in a ranke, 100000. footmen, and by their ſides for wings 40000. horſemen, ſo that he came to the combate with 240000. fighting men, well accompliſhed in armes: then was the great Turke carried vnder a goodly canapy vpon a blacke Waggon on mens ſhoulders into the Ferry, which was richly prepared, where in the view of both Campes he landed, whileſt the warlike inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ecchoed wide in the Aire. In the Iſland for Iudges ſat (in armour as did the other) the king of Rhods and the king of Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philia, now called <hi>Alcayr.</hi> When the Turke was landed there was brought to him by the hands of two kings a gret Elephant of an Aſhe colour white emboſſed very glittringly, where on the great Turke mounted by a ſhort ladder of ſiluer, armed verye ſtrongly and moſt beautifully, then tooke hee his Iauelin in his hand, and vibrated it in great brauery (as hee coulde handle his weapon well) and hung his quiuer of long Dartes at his backe, then his cemiter &amp;c. and ſo hauing ſaluted the Iudges retirde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vttermoſt part of the field, then mounted vp the braue and puiſſant Emperour ſo lightly in his heauy armour, as if eyther his gladneſſe had leſſened his waight, or the goodnes of his cauſe, to the great reioyſing of the Chriſtian and amazement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> turk,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:30"/> at whome the Chriſtians yeld ſo vniuerſallye and hallowed, and other infinit kinds of gladſome tokens that the Turke aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtood ſtone ſtill till the Chriſtian had done, &amp; then as men new riſen to life, with ſuch an horrible ſhout, that their voice reboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the aire, at which ſame time the Chriſtian ſhouted againe with them, as if they would haue committed a battell with voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſurely their voices did fight in the wide coaſts &amp; ſhoares of the aire. This done the Emperours prepared themſelues to the fight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>The Combate, CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <p>ANd when they were ſworne that neither of them had any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke hearbe, charme or incantation wherby they might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in their fight on their aduerſary, and had ſolemnized the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomable ceremonies in like matters of combat. The Herralds gaue their words of encounter, then with loude voice and ſhrill Trumpets couragious blaſt, whileſt all the people were in dead night expecting the demeanour of theſe renowmed Princes. Now we haue brought you to behold theſe two champions, arriued thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their braue followers, ready to proue their valiaunce in the face of ſo great a multitude. Now if you will ſtand aſide leaſte their ragged ſpeares endamage you, I will giue you leaue to look through the Lattice, where you ſhall euen now ſée the two Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours with their braue ſhocke, preſſe Doubt betwixt their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell encountrings. Now you may ſée the two combattants, or but as yet champions, comming from the ends of the field, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Chriſtian Emperour with incomparable valour, viſiting his Horſe ſides with his ſpurs, carrying his ſpeare in the reſt with an euen leuell, ſo that the thundering of the braue Stéede preſaged y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dint of the great thunderclap. When <hi>Ali Chan,</hi> gently galloping with his huge beaſt came forward with more ſwift pace ſtill as he drew nearer to the Emperour. All this while you may behold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haſtening in their courſe, like as you ſée two great waues gallop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from the corners of the ſea driuen by contrary windes, mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together by long randome, to make the neighbours ſhoares to quake and dimbde with their boyſterous carrier. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour being now with his greateſt fury ready to faſten his launce vppon his aduerſary, and his aduerſary ready to faſten his Iaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin
<pb facs="tcp:178202:31"/> on him, when the Turke ſuddainely ſtept aſide, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour thruſted his voide launce into the Aire, (for he mought ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely do it, for though the Elephant be but low, yet he was higher then his horſe by a yard, and yet his horſe was the faireſt and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt to be found in all Chriſtendome, ſo that néedes hee muſt laye his ſpeare in an vneuen height to breake it on him. Sodainely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turke ſtopt and with his nimble Beaſt followed the Emperour as he had fled, whereat all the whole army of Turkes ſhowted horribly clapping their hands, &amp; the Chriſtian ſtood ſtill in great ſilence, ſtroken with iuſt wonder of this ſtrange <hi>Quidity</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and ere the Emperour could make his ſtoppe with a ſhorte turne, the Turke had hit him vpon the ſhoulder with his Iaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin, which being denide entraunce, for very anger rent it ſelfe in forty péeces, and chid in the Aire till they broake their neckes on the ground: and had not then the Horſe ſtarted the monſtrous E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephant had ouerthrowne him with his rider to the earth. But then the Horſe incenſt with ire for this iniury, and his maiſter more hotely burning with diſdaine and furious gall, leapt, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſent out at his mouth the fomy arguments of his better ſtomacke, but ſo faſt the vile Turk followed that he had ſpent 3. long Darts vpon the barbed flanckes of the Horſe, which all in vaine returned to their Maiſter. The beholding Turkes ſo eger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purſuing the ſtroaks with ſhouting, as if with a hidden <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy</hi> their trayning had augmented the violence of the blowes. At le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth the good Emperour ſorely aſhamed came now to make him amends for his pretty falſery: and with great ſcope throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his lance forward iuſt vpward vppon the Turkes face, and when he was almoſt by him, the Infidel as if he but made a ſport of the fight, ſtept aſide very deliuery, thinking that he ſhould haue made him run in the like order as before, but hee more cautelous marking of purpoſe which way he ment to decline, turned with him and his learned Horſe could well doe it, and indéede deſire of reuenge had ſo ſeated it ſelfe in his braue couragious breaſt, that now he euen followed him as he had béene drawne with Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes, the Turke ſéeing how he was circumuented, fetcht a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty compaſſe and troad a round, the Elephant flying from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horſe and the horſe following the Elephant, as you might ſée <hi>Seignior Propſpero</hi> lead the way in <hi>Mile end Greene</hi> in the ringles, this
<pb facs="tcp:178202:31"/> was a pretty ſport to ſée the matter turnd to a play. Nowe the Chriſtians hauing like occaſion to ſhew their gladnes, gaue ſuch an <hi>Applaudite</hi> as neuer was heard in any Theater, laughinge ſo effuſedly that they daſht their aduerſaries cleane out of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, tickling againe with the long loud laughter: When they had run not paſſing twice about, the Turke ſéeing his time, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaied himſelfe out of the ring, and then got againe on his backe, ſpending his cowardly Darts vppon his ſtrong enemies armor, and ſo faſt he followed and ſo quickely the good Emperour turned backe againe, that his horſes barbe of Stéele out ſtickinge in his front, met iuſt vppon the out ſide of the right eye of the Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that it ſticking out a foote entred in aboue an inche, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horſe perceiuing made the reſt follow into his head vp to the hiltes (as to ſay) laying out his fore féete out ſtraight, and his hinder legs in like manner, went poaking, and crowded himſelfe forewarde ſtill gathering vppon the Elephant, ſo that not ſo much with the Horſes force as the great beaſts cruell pain, the Elephant ſwaid backe aboue 100. foote. Now was the Emperour glad and with both his hands lifting himſelfe vppon his ſtirrops, tooke his lance and ſtroake with the point the Turke full on the viſard ſo thicke and ſo many times, that ſome bloud followed, with an hue and cry out of the windowes of the Helmet, to find the worker of his effuſion: till the villaine ſlaue drawing his fine ſword ſmoate the launce very brauely in two, and caſting his ſhield afore him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the laſt ſtroake on the truncheon of it, which the gentle Emperour with fell fury threw at him, that he made him decline almoſt to the fall. The Turke ſitting on the Elephants backe could not with his Semiter reach the Chriſtian, nor he the Turk with his Curtilax, ſo that now they ſate and lookte one vpon the other, and the people at them, and all at this ſtraunge copeing. The good Horſe <hi>Grauntier</hi> by chaunce being gored a little vnder the maine betwixt the bendings of the barbs with the ſharp tusk of the Elephant, neied with great ſtomacke, and leaſinge from the beaſt which he had welnigh forced to the liſts end, being ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to forwarded with the ſharpe ſpurs with ſo excéeding fury, that it was not onely a maruell how the good Prince could ſit him ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly, and alſo that he ſpoild not himſelfe, and with more eager fury began to gallop vppon the Elephant again, his mouth wide
<pb facs="tcp:178202:32"/> open, and horrible with the ſalt fume which in aboundance iſſued from his great heart: for by how much the more a thing is gentle and quiet, by ſo much the more being moued he is iracund &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable. But the Emperor turning his rayns carried him clean contrary to the liſts end, where ſtood launces for the ſame purpoſe as the manner is, of which he chooſe the two ſtiffeſt, longeſt, and rudeſt for their ſtature and came ſoftly pacing to the Turke: who ſtoode euen there ſtill where hee was the Elephant bléedinge in ſunch abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance, that by the loſſe of ſo much bloud his méekenes turnd into rage, and began to riſe and bray, and ſtamp, and with an vncertaine ſway to moue, ſo that with much adoe the Slaue ſtaied and appeaſed him, then the braue Emperour lifting vp his viſour not onely to take breath but the more fréely that his ſpéech might haue paſſage, he told the Turke that he had in a baſe cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly manner by falſe fraud and vnequall fight diſhonored him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and endangerd him, for which he told him <hi>Malgrado ſuo</hi> he would be gloriouſly reuenged: and now that they had ſpent a good time in vncertaine Fortune, hee had brought two launces chooſe which he would, and either begin the fight a new or make an end of the old, promiſing vppon his Honor that if he refuſed ſo to doe, he would faſten one in his beaſt and another in his heart. And if hee dared to doe that, hee bad him come downe on foote and there breake a ſtaffe with him. The Turke as he was an Honorable ſouldier then preſently ſlipt of his Elephant, brauely anſwering that hee came to conquer him in ſport, and not meaning to make a purpoſed battaile, but ſith hee was ſo preſumptuous as to dare him to his face, he ſhould ſoone perceiue how lightly he wayed his proud words, and then skipping to him ſtraight a Launce out of his hand, and went 100. paces backewards, ſo did the Emperor very ioyfully, when they were come ſo far as they thought, they might truſt to their breath, houlding their Launces in both their hands, began to run very ſwiftly, and deſire brought them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo faſt and outragiouſly, that their Lauces ſomwhat too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapert not ſuffering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come together hurld the Turke aboue ſeuen féete of the Lances length, ſo that not one there but thought he had béene either ſlaine, or his winde daſht out of his belly: the Prince réeld backeward aboue two paces and yet fel down much aſtoniſhed. The people on both ſides excéedingly amazed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:32"/> eſpeciallye the Turkes who ſent out ſuch a dolefull <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untus</hi> that it would haue moued the ſtones to ruth, but the dolor of the Chriſtian was not ſo great for the mouing of the Emperor reuiued their ſpirites much. In a cauſe on which the behoulders ſafeties doe depend the ill ſucceſſe is much feared, for it maye bee ſéene by this, that they wil with a certaine alacrity and Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſéeme to helpe or to pitty as the cauſe requires. On a ſoddain the Emperour lift vp his head, at which the Chriſtians gaue ſuch an vniuerſall ſhoute, as if euen nowe they would paue frayed the mountaines adiacent. The two couragious beaſts hauing lately heaped vp red hote rancor in their diſdainefull ſtomackes, aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the one the other with all the weapons of nature, that it had béene enough for to haue delighted anye one, but the Horſe had ſome ſmall aduantage by reaſon of the Elephants right eye was couered with the trayling downe of the bloude. By this time the Emperours roſe againe, and the one went to his Horſe the other to his Elephant, hauing firſt ſplintered their ſpeares, and fenced ſo long as any vertue remained in the ſlaughtered Launces. When each had gotten to their beaſts they beganne to forwarde them, who with equall ire moued néeded no encouragement, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did the Emperour comming with ful ſcope vpon the Turk, ſmoat the Elephant iuſt vppon one of the téeth, while with greate rage the Horſe had faſtned his pike again in the Iaw bone, ſo that the Elephant ſtill ſwayed backe, but neither of them being able to reach the one the other, the excellent Prince caſting his goulden ſhield before him and drawing his glittering Curtelax, leapt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the necke of his Horſe, and laying one hande vppon the one tooth of the Elephant, with the other hand vpon the thong, that went croſſe his forehead, vauted vp and ſetling his féete vpon the tuskes and his hand on the head of the beaſt, caſt vp himſelfe, and laide his ſitting place where his hands were, and there rode by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and a little till he might buckle with the inſedent. No ſooner came he within the reach of the Turke, but hee ſmote the Turke ſo fréely, who was ready prepared for him that hee made him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline a little, there they fought ſo long that the Elephant driuen through paine was thruſt vp to the liſts, hereupon all the people Chriſtian in a more frée manner then euer at any time before, all the while their hard mettald ſwordes plaied vppon eache others
<pb facs="tcp:178202:33"/> ſhield, ſo that the glory of their rare fight was ſo wonderfullye pleaſing to the eie, and ſo honorable to the combattants, that if they had teſted one would well haue béene contented to viewe all the long day: but the good Prince was too hard for the other, for with his ready blowes he vrged the great Slaue out of his cell, &amp; made him ſit behinde the arſonne of the ſaddle, and if this chance had not happened he had ſurely made him ſit behinde the arſonne of his Elephantes Taile. For as ſoone as the Elephant had but touched the liſts, the Chriſtian Marſhals of the field came gallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and parted the Combattants, holding the Turke as van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, whileſt betwixt the contrary and aduerſe part ther was foure <hi>Negatiues,</hi> ſo that welnigh they had fallen to blowes, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe ſéemed to the Chriſtian plaine, to the Turke vniuſt. That becauſe the Beaſt whereon he rode went to the Liſts end, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtopper ſhould be blamed. Well, Herraldes whoſe office it is to deale in ſuch royall matters, had the diſcuſſing of it, and it was deferred to arbiters, with this condition, that if the Turke was found vanquiſhed, he ſhould be yéelded as recreant (&amp; miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant he was.) So the matter was poſted of whileſt it neuer was concluded, and both the parties departed, the one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> camp the other to the citty, in no leſſe ſolemne pompe then they entred accompanied into the ſands, where ſo rare a chaunce fortuned betwixt ſo puiſſaunt Emperours. And becauſe the matter was as ſtrange as trew, I haue ſoiourned a little too long in it. But in the next Inne you ſhall haue a better refreſhment or a newer choiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <p>BY chaunce a Knight ſmoate <hi>Fauſtus</hi> a boxe on the eare in the preſence of a great company of braue Ladies, wherefore hee ſwore to be egregiouſly reuenged on him, giuing him the Field, which the knight refuſed not, ſo the weapons, the place, the time were ordained, and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went out to the field, and no ſooner was <hi>Fauſtus</hi> gone out of the preſence but <hi>Signior di Medeſimo</hi> who was well knowen to be a valorous and couragious man in his kinde as any was about the Court, on a ſoddaine fell downe on his knées before all the Ladies, ſhaking and quiuering with a face as pall as him which was new riſen from a moneths bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:33"/> deſiring them if euer they tendred any Gentlemans caſe, to intreate <hi>Mounſier Infeligo</hi> to forgiue him his treſpaſſe. At this the whole aſſembly burſt out into a lowd laughter, to ſée the man that was euen now in his braue tearmes &amp; vanting words to come in all ſubmiſſiue manner to intreate for a pardon ſo ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly. He yet not deſiſting with many a ſalt teare and handes lifted vp toward the Heauens, from whence his pitty came, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Fauſtus</hi> came blowing in like aſwaſh-buckler with his Rapier by his ſide and his hand on his Poynard, ſwearing all the croſſe row ouer. But when he ſaw the Knight in ſuch a pickell, he ſatte himſelfe againſt a wall and laught ſo loude and ſo heartely, that all the whole rout could not chooſe, but laughe with him, and here was laughing, and here and ther and euery where. At length 2. Ladies roſe to whom perhaps this knight owed ſome particular ſeruice, and deſired <hi>Don Infeligo</hi> with very milde ſermon to bee friends with <hi>Medeſimo</hi> again, he told them that they could not demaund the thing which he would not readily fulfill, marry he requeſted this, that as the diſgrace which hee had receiued was too great to bee forgotten without ſome ſuch equall reuenge, that he might vſe ſome like iniury, whereby he might be ſatisfied and he might againe come into his grace: which they graunted. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> came to <hi>Medeſimo</hi> and reard him vp vppon his féete, &amp; then got vppon his baccke, and ſo rid twice about the Chamber, and when he had done he tooke him by the chin, who had not yet forgotten how to wéepe, ſhaking worſe then any ſchoole boy whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he feares to clime the horſe, and gaue him a good boxe on the eare and went his way. So the Knight was vtterly diſgraced, and for ſhame durſt not be ſéene all that day after. They which were ther had ſport aboundance, and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was feared for his braue valour and with his continuall delight in knauerye got him foes enough to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIIII.</head>
               <p>ANother time he by chaunce ouer hearde a Gentleman which was talking to a Lady, and ſayde that whatſoeuer ſhée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded him to doe hee woulde doe it, if ſhée would graunt him grace. The Gentlewoman belike willing to heare him ſpeake, ſo not to her required him to build in that place with one worde a
<pb facs="tcp:178202:34"/> Caſtle of fine ſiluer, at which the Gentleman amazed went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way confounded, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> followed him faſt, and ſayd to him that he had ouer heard the Ladies vniuſt demand, wherefore goe ſay (quoth he) thou wilt doe it with one word. And ſo the Gentleman did and it was done, whilſt he ran laughing in to many nobles &amp; luſty gallants, telling them he would ſhew them the ſtraungeſt thing that euer they ſawe, &amp; all they came running into the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den together, where they founde the Gentleman faſt lockte in a paire of ſtockes, &amp; an vgly fowle kitchin wench in his armes. O Lord what wondrous ſport did he make them there. And when they had laughed their fill, he lewſd the gallaunt, who went and ſwore all that he could he would bee reuenged on him. In ſuch monſtrous intollerable knaueries <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke eſpecial felicity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXV.</head>
               <p>THeſe foure honeſt fellowes <hi>Fauſtus, Akercock, Mephoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philes,</hi> and <hi>Wagner</hi> went out together into the ſtréete, and walking there by chaunce eſpied foure Gentlewomen ſeeming to be ſiſters, them they caſt to abuſe, and they were neuer content to play any merry pranckes for honeſt ſport, but they muſt be ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirically full of gall, that they commonly proued infamous, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring neither their good name on whom they committed them nor any kind of villany, ſo it might procure mirth: when they had tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſufficiently with them, they did ſo much that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ride abroad with them, and ſo each fetched his horſe and came to them masked, &amp; the Gentlewomen were wimpled like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (for the men as well as women vſe there to were maskes.) Thus they rode to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon furlong where many Italian gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen were playing at the <hi>Baloun,</hi> and there they rode round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout whole armies of ſhouts accompanyng them, they riding ſtil backward and forward, whilſt theſe men women had ſowed their coats to their dublets, and pind vpon their backes thinges of vile reproch amongſt them, then rode they to the Court not yet ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, wher they were entertained with more merriment &amp; laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And when theſe men-women ſaw the greateſt multitude that was there likely to be, euen vppon a péece of grounde which was higher then all the reſt, they leapt down, &amp; by reaſon of the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betwixt their peticoats and their doublets, they haled them al
<pb facs="tcp:178202:34"/> downe one after another, the horſes ran away, and they lay vpon them to their great confuſion &amp; reproch, yet they thought al well ſith they were perſonated and masked, but the women ſtripte off their womens garmentes and their head attires, and there they were well knowen to be foure braue noble yong Gentlemen bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ech of them rent off the maskes of <hi>Meph.</hi> &amp; his mates, and detected them to their gret ſhame, who neither durſt reuenge themſelues for feare of further diſpleaſure, nor of reuealing what they were, nor could be moaned of any one for their notable abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes afore hand, ſo that where as in others it had béene but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ieſt, on them it was wonderfull ſtrange and ridiculous. So they with ſhame enough went fretting in vaine to their lodging.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI.</head>
               <p>THe Emperor being ſome 5. or 6. daies in reſt within his wals muſed as floath cannot dwell in true noble breaſts, the whole Army to ſet forward, leauing a conuenient Garriſon within the Citty of 30000. men, marched into the fields in ſundry embat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tails with aboue 130000. men. And there in the view of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my <hi>Meph. Aker. Wag. Fau.</hi> prickt vp to the Turkes campe, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in compleat harnes, and there challenged any foure to break a ſtaffe with them, then came their forth four <hi>Ianiſſaries</hi> horeſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> armed at all aſſaies, and there they ran altogether to the ſingular delight of the beholders, ſo gallantly they demeaned themſelues, but in the cope all the 4. <hi>Ianiſſaries</hi> were runne quite throw, and throw (as they ſay) &amp; there lay on the could earth, then made theſe 4. fellowes in Arms their ſtop and expected a freſh reuenge: which came immediatly thundering out of the entry of the Campe, with whom to occur in time they met with the like ſucceſſe as before, to their ſingular commendations &amp; high praiſes: then gan the Turk to ſtampe and fret, and commanded foure of the beſt in his whole campe, and foure more with them to run at theſe villaines and to captiue them, where they ſhould rue the raſhnes of their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with long eternall torment. Theſe 8. came with all their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer together &amp; broake their lances very hardly vpon their faces, and ſo did they 4. on theirs, then they drew their ſwords commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a braue turnay, till two of the Turks were ſlaine, and the 6. fled, which were immediatly hanged, at which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laughed
<pb facs="tcp:178202:35"/> heartely, and theſe four returned thanked highly, and for that the Enemy would not aduance himſelfe to the generall Fortune of the fight, they marched in againe into the Citty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII.</head>
               <p>ABout 2. a clocke in the night the Turke approached with all his whole army vnto the wals of the citty, cauſing particular bands and Pyoners to dig through the countermure, the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels which were on the wals priuily eſpying by reaſon the Moon gaue ſome ſlender lighte, though ſhée was but thrée dayes olde, gaue warning without any alarme to the chiefe commaunders. ſo that the whole power of the Cittye almoſt was gathered into Armes, without any ſtroake of the Drum. The place wherein the turke was entring, was right againſt a ſtréets end of aboue two yards ouer and not aboue thirty yards from the breach, they had digged a déep trench and placed on the ſcarfe nine double ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons throughly round and charged with chaine and murderinge ſhot, and on each ſide of the croſſe ſtréete they had erected fortes of grauell &amp;c. like our Barricadoes now, in each of which they placed aboue fiftéene Culuerin and Cannon. Now the brech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficient the Turke hauing entred aboue 2000. men gaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onſet, and ſounded the bloudy alarm, when ſodainely the Flanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers diſcharged and the bulwarkes ſhot fréely together, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly cut of all them that entred beyond the ditch, &amp; betwixt thoſe thrée mentioned Forts with their terrible ſhot, they ſwept them all out of the place, then began the Turke to thruſt his men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vppon the breach (hauing loſt in this aſſault aboue 2100.) and euer as they came vp to the breach the Cannon heaued them of, and the ſmall ſhot fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loopes, ſo galled them that they durſt not approach. But the Turke cared not, for the murthering of his men, might weary the Cannons inſatiate cruelty at length. Then was the alarme giuen through the Citty, and euery one fell to their Arms, getting to the wals, and the reſt to the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling places, whileſt the Turke freſhly filled the breaches with murthered men, he enforcing himſelfe to his power to enter, and they to kéepe him out. When he ſaw that how hee had ſtopt the breaches ſo with dead bodies, which almoſt made a newe red ſea with their bloud, in a great rage tranſporting aboue 30000. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178202:35"/> ouer the Danubie, furniſhed them with ſcaling ladders, whilſt he with great ſtore of cannon beate his owne ſlaine men off the forenamed breaches, for he was a mercileſſe tyran, &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to aſſault the wall it ſelfe, which they did. Nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the morning to appeare, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Chriſtian</hi> came iuſt vppon the backs of the aſſailants, with the greateſt part of the whole power of the citie, and put them al to the ſword, ſaue thoſe that eſcaped from them by water, but killed of their owne felows. Then the Chriſtian marched vpon the Turke, who ſéeing his power greatly weakned, hauing loſt at his vnluckie aſſault a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 23000. men, curſing and banning his diſaſtrous fortune, and his Gods the giuers of it, retyred in a flying pace to his campe, whilſt the plentious ſpoile made rich the Chriſtian, for vpon the dead carcaſes were found ſtore of iewells and golde in great plentie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 28.</head>
               <p>THis new victorie gladded the Chriſtians excéedingly, as much as it grieued the Turke. The breaches now were freſhly repayred with all expedition. The Chriſtian Princes ſéeing the inconuenience that followed their kéeping within the citie, and how great ſhame it were for them to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from the enemie, conſidering their power to be not much inferior to that of the Turks in number, much more in braue ſouldierie, wherefore they made a generall muſter, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to offer the battell to them in the plaine field, which if they refuſed, they would giue them in their campes, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all vnder one dayes valiaunce, then marched foorth the Engliſh archers, of whom <hi>Wagner</hi> deſired he might bée with his fellowes, which when they had taken theyr ſtond, they brought ſtore of fletcherie to them in cartes, which were there diſburdened, ſo euerie archer beeing fiue double furniſhed, the number of them now was nine thouſand, the pike being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into them, being thereto deſirous, and hauing therfore made great ſuite, for the Emperour was verie loth to forgoe theyr firſt good ſeruice: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> counſelled the Captaine to chuſe a plot of aboue one hundreth akers ſquare, where it was open to each horſe man, which they meruailed at greatly, but
<pb facs="tcp:178202:36"/> yet they eaſily granted to ſtand anie where: they were ſo wel placed, that they ſtood as wel to defend the friend, as to offend the foe. Then in due order marched out the whole enemies of the Chriſtian, and ſo ſetteled themſelues, whileſt the Turke brought forward his thicke ſwarmes. Now it had bin a braue ſight, to ſee the greateſt princes of the whole worlde Eaſt and weſt, attended on by theyr whole forces ſet in araie, theyr gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous and bright armours and weapons caſting vp long tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels of golden ſhine to the heauens, the noiſe of clarions, trum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pets, &amp;c. incouraging the fainting ſouldier, and increaſing the boldnes of the reſolute There was at once in this field all the terrour of the world, accompanied with all the beautie. In the Citie you might haue ſéene the remainders at the churches at prayer, ſolemne proceſſion round about the towne with great deuotion, &amp;c. Well, the time was come that the horſemen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to aſſault the pike, and attempting the ruptures of theyr araie, and the forlorne hoaps fiercely ſkirmiſhing, whilſt with loude outcries the whole vſe of hearing was taken away: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue you nothing but ſmoake, round about you the thundring cannon, and ſharpe horrors of ſundrie weapons, and at your féet death. There might you ſée the great vſe of the eughen how for the horſe no whit fearing the muſket, or caliuer, as vſed to it, nor yet reſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the pearcing of a bullet, by the thick tempeſt of arrowes, hiding their eyes, and hurting their bodies, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the horſe maſter to the ground, on that ſide could not one horſe man appeare, but ſtraight they fetch him downe, ſo that of thirtie thouſand horſemen of one aſſault, there was not one that came within fiue ſpears length of the battel on foot. The great Turke curſing heauen and earth, and al trées that bore ſuch murthering fruit as bowes and arrowes, cauſed a troup of fiue hundreth barbed horſe with twentie thouſand more to runne vpon the archens altogether, which they did, but when they came iuſt vpon a little ridge, not one horſe but ſodaynely ſtopt, and the riders which now had reſted their ſtones, lying cloſe vpon the ſaddle pommels, were throwen quite out of the ſaddle, and either their backes broken, or quite ſlaine. All the whole archerie with the camp wondering hereat, as ignorant of the matter, euerie one ſuſpending his ſeuerall iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:178202:36"/> but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> laughed heartily, who knew the matter plaine, for there had they buried in ſand all the waie wolues guts, which by naturall magicke, as authors affirme ſuffers not the horſe to come ouer it in anie caſe, nor any force can carrie him ouer with a rider on him. For the Archers drue iuſt vpon, and ſo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſally ſhot together, that all the troups were put to flight, and aboue halfe ſpoiled and murthered. To be briefe, ſo much the Chriſtian preuailed vpon the Turke in thrée houres and a halfes fight, that all them were turnd and fled, each one ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing forward in his flight, there were ſlaine in this battel &amp; flight aboue ſeuen ſcore thouſand Turkes, the great Turke himſelfe fighting manfully on his Elephant, was by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors owne handes ſlayne, all his chiefe Baſſas and men of honour, to the number of thrée hundred died manfully about him: now the retrait was ſounded, and they marched home in moſt glorious pompe and reioycing, where the ſoldiers made rich with the great ſpoile of the campe, were diſmiſſed, and the princes returned home, and due order taken for the ſafetie of the citie. So the Duke of Auſtria rid of his enemies, gaue him ſelfe to his forepaſſed life, and the other princes with great ioy cauſed generall feaſts and triumphs to be performed in all theyr kingdomes, prouinces, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
